<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:opensearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearch/1.1/" xmlns:s="http://jadedpixel.com/-/spec/shopify">
  <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog.atom</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog.atom"/>
  <title>Ross Street Roasting Co. - Roaster&apos;s Blog</title>
  <updated>2021-06-15T18:31:53-05:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Ross Street Roasting Co.</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/freezing-coffee-i-would-do-anything-for-coffee-but-i-won-t-do-that</id>
    <published>2021-06-15T18:31:53-05:00</published>
    <updated>2021-06-15T18:31:53-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/freezing-coffee-i-would-do-anything-for-coffee-but-i-won-t-do-that"/>
    <title>Freezing Coffee: I would do anything for coffee, but I won’t do that…</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><em>[Note: This is a guest post by longtime RSR fan from Omaha, Spencer Gaskell. A few weeks back I saw him documenting his experiences with freezing coffee <a href="https://twitter.com/SpencerMAV" target="_blank" title="Spencer Gaskell on Twitter" rel="noopener noreferrer">on twitter</a> so I asked him to prepare this writeup on the experience, which he graciously did. Thanks, Spencer!]</em></p>
<p>What’s something in the coffee world you’ve experienced that seemed wrong in theory, but somehow works? Maybe it is some weird flavor combination, or perhaps it is an odd preparation method. Whatever the case, if you dive deep into coffee, chances are, you’ll have an experience like this eventually. And if you’re a fellow coffee nerd already, it’s probably happened over and over again.</p>
<div style="text-align: start;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/coffee-freezer-2-1024x576_600x600.jpg?v=1623799061" alt="" style="float: none;"></div>
<p><br><br>Freezing coffee is a terrible idea, right? Coffee is best 5 days to 3 weeks off roast. You have to grind fresh, use good water, and follow specific parameters. There’s no way you can just toss coffee in the freezer and forget about it for a year and still be able to enjoy it. Right? Riiiiight?? <em>[Editors note: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-steps-to-brewing-better-coffee" title="RSR Guide: 3 Steps to Brewing Better Coffee">He's right</a>]</em><br><br>Enter pandemic. All of a sudden, going out to experience other people’s crazy coffee experiments gone well isn’t really an option. So what to do? Well, obviously the answer is to go down the rabbit hole of coffee content on YouTube!<br><br>You may have gathered by now that I’m gonna tell you it’s okay to freeze your coffee. And you’d be right. So, how do you do it correctly? The short and sweet answer is that you eliminate as much air as possible and freeze as cold as you are able. But I’ll outline my process here...</p>
<h3> The 6 Steps to Freezing Coffee (Well)</h3>
<ol>
<li>Buy coffee from your favorite roaster (i.e. Ross Street Roasting)</li>
<li>Divide coffee into two week portions and put into vacuum seal bags<br>(Wait 3-5 days after roast before you do this so you don’t have to wait for off gassing later)</li>
<li>Vacuum seal the coffee - This eliminates as much of the air as possible  and removes moisture potential. Freezers are dry, so they suck water out of the air and it forms ice, which then melts into your coffee when you defrost it</li>
<li>Put the sealed bags of coffee in the freezer - A deep freezer is great. Colder freezers slow the oxidation, loss of aromatic compounds, etc. more than a domestic freezer</li>
<li>When you’re ready for more coffee, take a bag out of the freezer the night before you want to use it. Let it defrost overnight before opening.</li>
<li>Open, grind, brew, enjoy.</li>
</ol>
<p><br>Suddenly, there are no limitations to when you buy coffee! Think special releases, sale prices, or your new favorite coffee. Also, there’s no limit on how much of it you buy. Two pound bags? Absolutely! What about 5 pound bags? Not just for wholesale anymore! In fact, there’s no point in freezing the coffee if you only buy one normal sized bag at a time.<br><br>Shortly after discovering I could freeze coffee (April 2020), I stocked up with a two pound bag of the Gold Mountain Brix Breaker from Nicaragua, one of the award winning coffee’s from Ross Street. I had purchased some in November 2018 (and ordered more in September 2019), and it checked all the boxes for coffees I love. It was a fruit bomb, natural processed coffee with sweetness for days. Once the bulk bag showed up, I packaged it up and stuck it in the freezer. But then I got other coffees and did the same thing. At some point, I reorganized the freezer. All of a sudden, one bag of it ended up at the bottom of the stack. But, eventually it got discovered, albeit a whole year later. So what do you do with year old frozen coffee? Well, when it’s really good, you open it up and try it out.<br><br><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/brix-vac-sealded_480x480.jpg?v=1623799532" alt=""><br><br>I’d seen enough information on freezing coffee along the way that I was fairly confident it was still going to be pretty drinkable. But it still seemed so wrong, so it was going to take actually experiencing this truth to accept it and tell other people.<br><br>After busting into it and brewing a cup, I immediately remembered how much I liked the coffee to begin with. I wish I had taken notes when I had it so long ago, to have a better reference point, but it was still a super sweet, super fruity, cup of happiness.<br><br></p>
<div style="text-align: start;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/coffee_set-up_600x600.jpg?v=1623799607" alt="" style="float: none;"></div>
<p><br><br>As I kept drinking it, it kept changing. Which reminded me I had a similar experience the other times I had this coffee. I’m not usually one to wax poetic with my tasting notes, but sometimes a great cup of coffee just speaks to you and the words start flowing. Blueberry hibiscus herbal tea. Fermenty brown banana note in the finish as the cup cools. Super complex, super fun, hard to put down, and I didn’t want to see it go.<br><br>Even though I had plenty of experience to be able to say freezing coffee works, I’m now fully convinced it is a great plan. I’ll continue to freeze coffee without worrying that I’m doing harm to my continual pursuit of the “perfect cup.”<br><br>A lot happened over the course of a year. It was a weird time living through a pandemic. But plenty of good things happened. I even bought an espresso machine and grinder. And yet, perhaps the best thing to happen to me was discovering how to freeze coffee.<br><br><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/mug_water_600x600.jpg?v=1623799689" alt=""></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-create-the-perfect-at-home-coffee-bar</id>
    <published>2021-03-12T14:21:20-06:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-16T08:56:06-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-create-the-perfect-at-home-coffee-bar"/>
    <title>How to Create the Perfect At-Home Coffee Bar</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Many can agree that nothing quite beats a freshly brewed cup of coffee in the morning and with all of the at-home brewing tools available these days there are more ways to go about making a cup of joe than ever. So having a dedicated space to brew and keep your equipment is essential. And while nothing can fully replicate the feeling of stepping into your favorite coffeehouse we’ve reached out to the coffee experts from </span><a href="https://www.redfin.com/city/16409/CA/Sacramento?utm_source=google&amp;utm_medium=ppc&amp;utm_term=kwd-331947829374&amp;utm_content=456626276547&amp;utm_campaign=1024451"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Sacramento</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to </span><a href="https://www.redfin.com/city/11458/FL/Miami?utm_source=google&amp;utm_medium=ppc&amp;utm_term=kwd-331947829374&amp;utm_content=456626276547&amp;utm_campaign=1024451"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Miami</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;"> to help you create the most authentic coffee shop experience possible with the ultimate home coffee bar.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/unnamed-1.jpg?v=1615580627" alt=""></span></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Start with a clean and tidy workspace</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">In order to create the perfect home coffee corner, there are a few things that you can simply not go without. First, is a clean and tidy workspace in order to create the blank canvas necessary to focus on your craft, which is producing the perfect cup of coffee. Coffee is both an art and a science and your cup of coffee is the experiment and the masterpiece all brewed into one beautifully edible treat. Second, you need some good tunes to accompany you while you brew. Everyone knows that what makes or breaks a coffee shop is their music. While there is no right or wrong choice when it comes to selecting music for your home cafe (after all you are your only audience) it's more about feeling the vibe of the day and choosing how you'd like to start it and with what artist you'd like to sing or dance along to. Finally, we recommend having some coffee table reads (National Graphic Magazine, NYT crossword puzzle, Drift Magazine, etc.) to enjoy when you finally sit down to sip your coffee in your home coffee corner, patting yourself on the back for being the owner, barista, customer, and metaphorical yelp reviewer after. You are a one-man/woman show and while there are a billion details that go into making a cup of coffee brilliant, the most important is how much fun you have while making it, and how it serves as a cup of calm before the storm of whatever your day might bring. Enjoy! - </span><a href="https://www.breckenridgecoffeeroasters.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Breck Coffee Roasters</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Give it a view</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When looking for a functional and comfortable coffee nook I look for two things: a window and accessibility to utilities. If you can look out a window while brewing your morning cup it's all the more reason to wake up in the morning! Make sure the location is accessible to water, trash, and electricity and you will be all set. - </span><a href="https://www.backyardbeans.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Backyard Beans Coffee Co.</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quality coffee is a must</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Freshly roasted coffee and a really good grinder (we suggest a Baratza Encore) will transform any home coffee experience. Making sure your grinder is on the appropriate setting will ensure the perfect cup. No matter the preferred brewing method, grind uniformity and fresh coffee will make any home coffee experience elevated. - </span><a href="https://barringtoncoffee.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Barrington Coffee </span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Support your local roasters</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Beyond the aesthetics that make up a cozy coffee nook, we feel the coffee you choose for your space is key. So, be sure to explore the many great local roasters in your area. Being a family-owned small business ourselves, we know how important it is to support local businesses. Partnering with local roasters and making their offerings accessible to offices across the greater Bay Area is just one of the many ways we deliver happiness! - </span><a href="https://associatedcoffee.com"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Associated Coffee</span></a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><span style="font-weight: 400;">[Check out our list of <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-best-specialty-coffee-roasters-in-iowa" title="The Best Specialty Coffee Roasters in Iowa">The Best Specialty Coffee Roasters in Iowa</a>!]</span></em></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Incorporate a free-standing cart</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Using a free-standing cart allows you to create a coffee corner anywhere in your home. Let it be the focal point of every party! Even add open shelving above your cart to store the coffee cups. Displaying them is not only convenient but stylish. - </span><a href="https://www.myrusticmodernliving.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">My Rustic Modern Living</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Think of your brewing tools as functional art</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A coffee brewing station is the best way to transform your kitchen into an in-home cafe. With manual brewing equipment - like a Hario V60, Chemex, Kalita Wave, and gooseneck kettle - it's easy to achieve form without losing functionality. You can even arrange your equipment on your countertop, floating shelves, or hutch in ways to make them showpieces. If you don't have that kind of space in your kitchen, manual brewing equipment is small enough to put that it doesn't take up a lot of space. Plus, you don't have to worry about the unsightly power cords of automatic brewers and grinders cluttering up your countertops. - </span><a href="https://thenoteworthy.blog/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Noteworthy</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Don’t skimp on the grinder</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">There are several important factors to creating the perfect home coffee bar. Believe it or not, you do not need fancy or expensive equipment. Just make sure you have a good burr grinder. The biggest thing that people overlook is water quality. Investing in a good water filtration system as well as finding a good local roaster will have you on your way to the best home coffee experience! - </span><a href="https://www.weirdbrothers.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Weird Brothers</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Regardless of whether you are brewing coffee on an espresso machine, drip brewer, or pour-over, a burr grinder is essential to every home coffee corner. This ensures the coffee is ground fresh and to a uniform size every time. This allows for an even extraction that makes every cup of coffee smooth and flavorful. We recommend our Dawn Patrol blend which is the perfect coffee every morning. - </span><a href="https://thewestbean.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">The West Bean</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Make it your own</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The best part of a coffee corner is that it is yours. It’s your own private coffee shop that you can experience a piece of the world in your home. A coffee corner does not need to be fancy- just let your style come alive or add character into your home through this space. Our home coffee corner has changed over the years. From a cute cart with our brew equipment and mugs hanging above it to mugs hanging in the kitchen above our makeshift island that holds all of the brewing equipment. Your coffee corner doesn’t need to be a literal nook or corner just use what you have and make it yours. Our essentials: A gooseneck kettle, a Chemex- for a group or our family’s multiple morning cups, a pour-over, a grinder, fresh and delicious coffee, and endless mugs. A coffee corner can become full fast so we suggest trying to keep it crisp and minimal. When you are hosting or making that first-morning cup, you don’t want to feel cluttered or dirty so try to keep the corner as minimal as possible. You’ll be surprised at how that cliche phrase of "less is more" can shine. -</span><a href="https://www.emeraldox.co/"><span style="font-weight: 400;"> Emerald Ox</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Invest in proper equipment</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">I would start with a dependable brewer.  I prefer one that uses a thermal pot so the coffee doesn’t burn from sitting on the burner.  I also like to grind my beans daily, so a small non-commercial grinder will do the trick.  I use the Bodum Bistro Grinder, which is perfect - Barnie’s sells this model on our website.  I suggest good porcelain mugs with a comfortable handle (maybe one that has a story). After all, your morning coffee routine should be an enjoyable experience. Lastly having quality coffee(s) is a must! - </span><a href="https://www.barniescoffee.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Barnie’s Coffee &amp; Tea Co.</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When creating the perfect coffee corner, you need to opt for the right coffee equipment, and it's hard to beat smart coffee machines. With smart machines, you'll be able to set scheduled coffee routines and get the most out of your mornings. There are many compact smart coffee machines on the market that can fit on a countertop and be paired with your phone or tablet to automate the brewing process so you can enjoy more of your breaks. - </span><a href="https://www.market-inspector.co.uk/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Market Inspector</span></a></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">We believe the best days begin with a delicious cup of coffee. Start your own morning coffee ritual with these few tips. Having the best coffee equipment is crucial; we suggest a burr coffee grinder and freshly-roasted coffee. Light, medium, or dark roast is up to you, but never compromise on freshly-roasted coffee beans! - </span><a href="http://commonwealthjoe.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Commonwealth Joe Coffee Roasters</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Regularly restock your beans</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Regularly restock your stash of freshly roasted, specialty-grade whole bean coffee.  Coffee peaks between three to seven days after roasting at which time it begins losing its flavor.  Do not grind your coffee until just before you use it as this dramatically accelerates the loss of quality and flavor.  No...storing your coffee in the freezer does not extend its shelf life! - </span><a href="https://quintessacoffeeroasters.com/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Quintessa Coffee Roasters</span></a></p>
<h1><span style="font-weight: 400;">Don’t neglect your water quality</span></h1>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">A cup of coffee is over 98% water, so it stands to reason that if you use bad water with good coffee, you run the risk of dragging your cup quality down. Use reverse osmosis or distilled water, then consider a mineral compound additive that's calibrated specifically for brewing coffee, such as </span><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/gifts-gear-more/products/third-wave-water-12-one-gallon-sticks-classic-profile" title="Third Wave Water"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Third Wave Water</span></a><span style="font-weight: 400;">. - Brian @ </span><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ross Street Roasting</span></p>
<br>
<p><em><a href="https://www.redfin.com/blog/how-to-create-the-perfect-at-home-coffee-bar/"><span style="font-weight: 400;">Originally published on Redfin</span></a></em></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;"> </span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-best-specialty-coffee-roasters-in-iowa</id>
    <published>2020-10-18T09:44:15-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-10-18T09:44:15-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-best-specialty-coffee-roasters-in-iowa"/>
    <title>The Best Specialty Coffee Roasters in Iowa (Updated for 2020)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian surveys the landscape of Specialty Coffee roasting in the state of Iowa. Current edition: 2019<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-best-specialty-coffee-roasters-in-iowa">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>When I started Ross Street Roasting Co. in 2015, I could count the number of Specialty Coffee roasters on one hand. Now 5 years later, I'm very close to needing an extra set of hands to count us!</p>
<p>And when the pandemic hit in March of 2020, it knocked the lives of everyone on the planet sideways, so of course COVID-19 has impacted coffee roasting businesses as well. We feel fortunate that our types of businesses were well-positioned to weather the storm. The fellow roasters that I've linked to below offer online ordering and shipping. By all means check them out and support us! Making coffee at home has become more commonplace this year, and there's an ample number of great coffee roasters in Iowa now.</p>
<p>Programming note: I'm focusing on roasters of <em>Specialty Coffee</em> in Iowa, and there is technical precision to that term. Specialty Coffee represents the top quality grades of coffee in the world, and are scored on a 100-point scale. All coffees that can be sold into the Specialty market must score at least 80 points or above. </p>
<p>So without further ado, here is <strong>my totally biased</strong> list of the Best Specialty Coffee Roasters in our home state of Iowa.</p>
<h2>Ross Street Roasting Co.</h2>
<p><em>Surprise!</em> Of course I think my own company deserves top billing! :) I like to think that we've done a great job of making Specialty Coffee accessible to a broader swath of the coffee drinking public. Since our founding, our mission has been to "Turn coffee drinkers into coffee <em>lovers.</em>" We are located in a small rural community, where old church ladies and farmers are accustomed to drinking nostalgic big brands from the mid-20th century (that still have considerable market share in these parts), and we've developed <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-and-tea" title="Shop Coffee &amp; Tea - Ross Street Roasting Co.">our expansive product catalog</a> to bring high-end coffees to "normal" coffee drinkers as well as "coffee snobs." </p>
<p>We consistently make new customers across rural Iowa, and get feedback like "I usually have to add cream or sugar to my coffee, but this tastes so good I don't have to add anything!" That's music to my ears and it's an indicator to me that we're making good on our mission statement. </p>
<p>Now that my totally biased #1 is out of the way, here are more awesome roasters in Iowa. I'll go in alphabetical order since I'm not trying to rank anyone...</p>
<h2>Capanna Coffee Roasters (North Liberty)</h2>
<p><a href="http://capannacoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="Capanna Coffee, North Liberty IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Capanna predates RSR by a good 9 years, so I've been fortunate to get to know owner/roaster Mike McCain and learned from his wisdom in the biz. Not only does Mike roast tasty coffee, but he also makes incredible gelato! If you're swinging by on I-380 between Iowa City and Cedar Rapids, it's totally worth the short jaunt east to get a coffee or espresso and some gelato!</p>
<h2>Dash Coffee Roasters (Cedar Rapids, Iowa City)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.dashcoffeeroasters.com/" title="Dash Coffee Roasters, Cedar Rapids IA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Owners Phil &amp; Rebecca burst onto the scene about 3 yrs ago with their Cedar Rapids roastery/café location, and have quickly expanded to two more retail locations in CR and Iowa City. Early on they hosted a latte art competition, which I competed in more for comedic value than anything. (I'm a roaster, <em>not</em> a barista! :) )</p>
<p>Since that time, Phil and I have become roaster buddies and chat regularly, swap coffees, and compare notes. I enjoy popping into their retail elegant cafés for coffee (and their food is great, too). In 2019, Phil saved my rear-end when a piece of metal got into one of our production grinders. He threw a set of new grinding burrs in his saddlebag, hopped on his motorcycle, and buzzed over to Tama to help me fix the grinder. The coffee community at it's best! </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Roasters Phil &amp; Brian" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/IMG_0936_large.jpeg?v=1576613923" style="float: none;"><br><em>Roasters Phil Davidson (Dash) &amp; Brian G. (RSR)<br>&amp; the Great Grinder Fix of Sept. 2019</em></p>
<h2>Euphoria Coffee (West Union)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.drinkeuphoria.coffee/" target="_blank" title="Euphoria Coffee, West Union IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Fellow rural, small-town roasters that have gone the route of roastery/café, which is <em>not</em> an easy business to pull off in struggling rural communities! Founder Nick Yost has become a roaster buddy of mine, as well. In 2019, he purchased a few bags of coffee from our Nicaraguan direct trade partners, Gold Mountain Coffee Growers, and I had the chance to drive those bags up to him and check the place out. In 2019 they also moved into a new building on the square in West Union and bought a larger drum roaster after winning a grant competition through the <a href="https://www.iowaeconomicdevelopment.com/MainStreetIowa" target="_blank" title="Main Street Iowa - Iowa Economic Development" rel="noopener noreferrer">Main Street Iowa</a> program. </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/IMG_0895_large.jpeg?v=1576614323" style="float: none;"><br><em>Roasters Brian G. (RSR) &amp; Nick Yost (Euphoria)</em><br><em>Dropping off direct trade Nicaraguan coffee</em></p>
<h2>Horizon Line Coffee (Des Moines)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.horizonlinecoffee.com/" title="Horizon Line Coffee, Des Moines IA">Website</a> - I love this story: In 2017, two young dreamers from Southern California moved to Des Moines specifically to start a café/roastery. Brad &amp; Nam and the HLC crew hosted a latte art competition early shortly before opening, which brought together the coffee community from across Iowa. It ended up getting them in a bit of trouble with the health inspectors (cart before the horse problem), but it also signaled their commitment to getting connected with the growing Specialty Coffee culture in Iowa. </p>
<p>HLC is one of my regular stops when I head to Des Moines. Conveniently located downtown, where there's all sorts of awesome people and food and drink businesses as well as a rapidly expanding residential base, HLC has become a staple business in the Western Gateway district of downtown Des Moines. They have a commitment to inclusivity, hospitality, and sustainability that are a model for the rest of us to aspire to. And Brad and Nam are just wonderful humans. (I only regret that I don't have a good photo of me and the two of them :) )</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<h2>Iris Coffee (Pella)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.iriscoffee.co/" target="_blank" title="Iris Coffee, Pella IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Founder Elizabeth D. had worked in the café environment prior to starting Iris, so she brings a wealth of experience from the commercial coffee shop world to her roasting business. She is also one of the few roasters in the state who, like us, roasts on a "fluid bed" type roaster - somewhat unique amongst the more common gas drum roasters. And finally, she's a woman roastery owner/operator, which is rare in the industry and awesome to see. </p>
<p>Elizabeth has visited our shop in Tama a few times, and we've exchanged notes on roasting technique since we share the same type of machine. Pella is close to where I grew up, so it's great to see craft coffee roasting taking root in that unique community started by Dutch Reformed immigrants (including my maternal great grandparents). </p>
<h2>Morning Bell Coffee Roasters (Ames)</h2>
<p><a href="https://squareup.com/store/morningbellcoffeeroasters" target="_blank" title="Morning Bell Coffee Roasters, Ames" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Founder Nadav is just a precious jewel of a human being. We connected a few years ago and before the end of our first conversation he said, "If you're ever in a pinch for coffee, let me know" - And I've had to take him up on that offer once! :) Their 2019 expansion on Old Main St. in Ames has given them a wonderful café space one the front of the building where you can see through a large plate glass window into the roast production area.</p>
<p>Nadav is also a wizard when it comes to cold brew, consistently cranking out <em>delicious</em> cold brew drinks flavored with natural ingredients. Paired with the lever-operated espresso machine on the bar, Morning Bell is an awesome place to hang out and get some great coffee in old downtown Ames.</p>
<p>I recently got a new job at a tech company in Ames, so I get to see Nadav on the regs now!</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/5C67BA07-7D18-4DD4-B29C-8126D687D17F_large.jpeg?v=1576678042" style="float: none;"><br><em>Roaster buddies Brian &amp; Nadav</em></p>
<h2>Sidecar Coffee (Cedar Falls/Waterloo)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.sidecarcoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="Sidecar Coffee, Cedar Falls / Waterloo IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Sidecar holds a special place in my heart because they got into the game before I did and I look up to them and the successful roastery/local café chain that they've set up in the CF/W'loo area. Roaster Jed and I have bumped into each other a few times at coffee events, including our shared sourcing partner in Minneapolis, Café Imports. </p>
<p>Sidecar was also the inspiration for me in the realm of barrel-aged coffees. Jed's was the first barrel-aged coffee I ever tried, I believe it was even before I started roasting. I don't get up to CF/Waterloo too often, but Sidecar is definitely a must-stop for me when I do!</p>
<h2>Stone Bru (Sioux City)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.stonebru.com/" target="_blank" title="Stone Bru - Sioux City, Iowa coffee roaster &amp; cafe" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Stone Bru is newer to me, and I came across them at the fall 2019 Siouxland Coffee Fest, where they were a major sponsor. After chatting with one of the owners, we did a bag swap and I got my hands on a natural process Costa Rican coffee of theirs and OH MY GOODNESS, it was fantastic. I <em>love</em> naturals, and this one did not disappoint. Sweet, fruity, juicy, delicious. We tore that 12oz bag at the shop in less than a week, which is pretty rare. They don't seem to have a website at this point, so if you're up in that part of the state, definitely check them out. If I'm remembering their story correctly, they started their life as a café and only recently got into roasting their own. If that's true, they're off to a great start in the roasting biz!</p>
<h2>Swed &amp; Co. Coffee (Fort Madison)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.swedandco.com/" target="_blank" title="Swed &amp; Co. Coffee" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - Founder Chris Swed has a delightful roastery way down in SE Iowa on the Mississipi River, where he sells direct to consumer through his website and also supplies a few grocery stores in that part of the state. He's also been able to make it to a number of coffee events closer to us, so we've bumped into him a few times. Great guy, roasting great coffee!</p>
<p>They also highlight local artists and photographers through their bag labels, which is a very unique touch with their products. Very cool!</p>
<h2>Windmill Coffee Roasters (Ames)</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.windmillcoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="Windmill Coffee Roasters, Ames IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> - These guys have become friends over the past year or so, and Andrew and Robb are knowledgable, kind, and fun to hang out with. I've had the chance to pop into their production space in time for a cupping session, which was a lot of fun. Our production grinder came from Andrew a few years ago after he rehabbed it with a new burr set (which was damaged in 2019, see story above). </p>
<h3>Honorable Mention</h3>
<p>There are a few that I didn't do write-ups on, but that's not due to any ill will on my part! Some up and comers that I'm not as familiar with, but y'all should definitely look out for...</p>
<ul>
<li>
<a href="https://www.blacksiloroasting.com/" target="_blank" title="Black Silo Roasting Co. - Altoona, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Black Silo Roasters</a>, Ankeny/Altoona - These guys started up a year or two after us and have the same model of roaster! So we've traded notes and questions over the years. They supply Porchlight Coffeehouse in Ankeny, where I have friends and family, so I enjoy popping in there for coffee when I'm in town.</li>
<li>
<a href="https://blkandbold.com/" title="BLK &amp; Bold, West Des Moines">BLK &amp; Bold</a>, West Des Moines - I found out about these guys through our design/branding consultant, Adam at Avidity Creative. Their one of his clients, and look to have an awesome social entrepreneurship model with a mission to promote "initiatives aligned to sustaining youth programming, enhancing workforce development, and eradicating youth homelessness"</li>
<li>
<a href="https://www.dreibergecoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="DreiBerge Coffee, Des Moines" rel="noopener noreferrer">DreiBerge Coffee</a>, Des Moines - Brand new roastery/café as of 2019, located in Des Moines' East Village. Great couple that owns it, awesome commitments to sourcing, roasting, and a great café atmosphere</li>
<li>
<a href="https://www.kojoroastery.com/" target="_blank" title="Kojo Roastery, Stacyville" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kojo Roastery</a>, Stacyville - I had to look up Stacyville, it's waaaay up in northern Iowa near the border of Minnesota. We purchased a bag from Kojo to feature at our Saturday Café Hours one weekend earlier this year, and it was a fundraiser coffee for one of the founders local friends. We haven't had a chance to connect with them yet, but they seem to be growing fast and off to a good start!</li>
<li>
<a href="https://www.lightbritecoffee.com/" title="Lightbrite Coffee Roasters - Grimes, Iowa">Lightbrite Coffee Roasters</a>, Grimes - I haven't had a chance to check these folks out yet but we have some mutual connections. As of 2020 they've opened a retail space on the NW side of Des Moines between Johnston and Grimes. </li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.wakeupiowacoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="Wake Up Iowa Coffee, Iowa City IA" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wake Up Iowa</a>, Iowa City - I've not run into these folks too often, but I have had a chance to chat with their roaster and he's a great guy. I believe they roast on a fluid bed roaster like us! </li>
</ul>
<p>That's my take on Specialty Coffee roasters in Iowa, folks! There are probably some that I missed, and I'm sorry for that. I intend for this to be a post that I update each year, so reach out to me with any additions and corrections. </p>
<p>Happy Roasting, fellow roasters - And happy brewing, Coffee Friends! </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/gold-mountain-coffee-growers-2020-origin-report</id>
    <published>2020-07-19T12:02:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-07-19T12:02:10-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/gold-mountain-coffee-growers-2020-origin-report"/>
    <title>Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - 2020 Origin Report</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Roaster Brian chats with Farmer Ben from Gold Mountain Coffee Growers in Nicaragua, our "relationship coffee" supplier for six consecutive harvest seasons! Ben takes us on a virtual mini-origin trip to show </span><span>what the coffee whole production process looks like there, and what makes Gold Mountain such a unique and awesome social enterprise that fights poverty with high-quality, award-winning </span><span>Specialty Coffee productio</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/gold-mountain-coffee-growers-2020-origin-report">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>In just over a month, fresh crop Nicaraguan coffees from our friends at <strong>Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</strong> will be arriving here in Iowa for the sixth straight year. Since it's been a year and a half since our last trip to visit the Gold Mountain crew, we decided it would be nice to check in with Founder &amp; CEO, Ben Weiner.</p>
<p>Ben takes us on a virtual mini-origin trip to show what the coffee whole production process looks like there, and what makes Gold Mountain such a unique and awesome social enterprise that fights poverty with high-quality, award-winning Specialty Coffee production. Check it out!</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/2Pu9HSZolwk" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<h3>Learn More about Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com/" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - Specialty Coffee from Nicaragua" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain's website</a></li>
<li>Gold Mountain on <a href="http://www.instagram.com/goldmtncoffee" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers on Instagram" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram</a> </li>
<li><a href="https://youtu.be/sgYoxg07sLU" target="_blank" title="Farmer Derek Klingenberg - 2019 Nicaragua coffee trip video" rel="noopener noreferrer">Farmer Derek hugs coffee farmers in Nicaragua!</a></li>
</ul>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-customer-satisfaction-results</id>
    <published>2020-03-15T12:31:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-03-15T12:32:00-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-customer-satisfaction-results"/>
    <title>RSR Customer Satisfaction Results 2020</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian summarizes our 2020 Customer Satisfaction survey results. Spoiler alert: They're great!<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-customer-satisfaction-results">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>A key part of any business is keeping a finger on the pulse of its customers and how they feel about you and what you do for them. It's something that we've done somewhat sporadically throughout our nearly 5 years in business, but I've implemented a more measurable and repeatable survey this year and I'm happy to share with everyone what our customers think about us. Hint: It's very positive. </p>
<p>We're in a fun business: We source awesome coffees, roast our orders fresh, and get that stuff out to our dear customers as fast as we can. We've worked hard to develop a fun, approachable Specialty Coffee brand that "turns coffee drinkers into coffee <em>lovers</em>." We've been doing it for almost 5 years, and it appears we're doing a pretty good job. </p>
<p>For our survey, we asked a simple question: <strong>On a scale of 0-10, how likely are you to refer RSR to a friend, family member, or colleague?</strong> - We sent this question to our active <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/pages/email-newsletter-signup" title="RSR email newsletter signup">email newsletter</a> subscribers (most of whom are active customers), and we got about a 12% response rate. Here are the results:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/RSR-CustomerSatisfaction-2020.png?v=1584291935" alt=""></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We consider anyone that gave us a 9 or 10 response to be active promoters of the RSR brand, and well...93.3% of the people that responded to the survey are in that category. That's amazing, people! </p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>(For any marketing pros out there, you'll recognize this survey and the scoring system as the NPS / Net Promoter Score. A score of 92 is epic.)</em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">We also asked 2 optional qualitative questions on the survey:</p>
<ul>
<li>What do you like about RSR?</li>
<li>What do you think we can do better?</li>
</ul>
<p>Responses to #1 were a blast to read. A number of people mentioned me, specifically. *blush* Gosh, thanks y'all! It's true that I've made myself a fairly integral part of the overall RSR brand. We did, after all, start in my garage on Ross Street in Toledo, Iowa, so our story of me going from a hobby roaster in a small rural community to a business that's continued to grow for our first 5 years, adding one job (so far) to our local economy, and helping raise the bar for Specialty Coffee in the state of Iowa (and beyond!) is something that connects with a number of our customers on a personal &amp; emotional level. It's inspiring to me to have you along on that journey with me, folks! </p>
<p>In the area of things we can do better, a lot of responses here were more praise. Some folks asked for free shipping all the time, which all e-commerce businesses are used to seeing thanks to You Know Who.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/IMG_2850_large.jpeg?v=1584292768" style="float: none;"><br><em>(It's funny 'cos it's true)</em></p>
<p>We received some good feedback on ways that we can make our <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-subscriptions" title="RSR Coffee Subscriptions">coffee subscription</a> system a bit more easy to use, which I'll be acting on. Somebody even suggested it would be cool if we offered sample packs and good news, my dude: We <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-and-tea/products/flight-of-fancy-single-origin-coffees-four-5oz-bags" title="Flight of Fancy: 4-Pack of Single Origin Coffees">have</a> <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-and-tea/products/sample-flight-blends" title="Sample Flight: Blends - 3-pack">two</a>! </p>
<p>The survey was offered anonymously, but each person was given the choice of providing their email address for me to follow up with them. We've always taken feedback very seriously and usually act on it in some way. We always at least respond to folks, which I take to be a must-do for quality customer service.</p>
<p>Well, that's it for the survey results for this year! We'll continue to issue this instrument annually, so we can start tracking our performance historically. It's this kind of commitment that we believe will give us another 5 years of success and growth in this awesome little business. </p>
<p>If you're a customer or social fan that didn't get a chance to complete the survey but would still like to give us some feedback, hop on over to the <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/pages/contact-us" title="Contact Us">Contact Us</a> page and send us your thoughts!</p>
<p>Thanks, coffee friends!</p>
<p><em>(Feature photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@lidyanada?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText" target="_blank" title="Feature photo credit: Lidya Nada via Unsplash" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lidya Nada</a> on Unsplash)</em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-brings-mighty-peace-coffee-from-the-dr-congo-to-iowa</id>
    <published>2020-02-22T15:35:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-02-22T15:57:05-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-brings-mighty-peace-coffee-from-the-dr-congo-to-iowa"/>
    <title>RSR brings Mighty Peace Coffee from the DR Congo to Iowa</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Introducing our new supply relationship with Mighty Peace Coffee, a social enterprise in the Democratic Republic of Congo!<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/rsr-brings-mighty-peace-coffee-from-the-dr-congo-to-iowa">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last month we quietly introduced a new permanent, year-round offering in our Single Origin Coffee category: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee/products/rise-up-peace-island-congolese-coffee" alt="Rise Up, Peace Island - Peace Trade Coffee from DR Congo">"Rise Up, Peace Island"</a> from the DR Congo - A light-medium roast with apple &amp; citrus fruit notes, sweet, and a heavy body.</p>
<p>But what we haven't done yet is talk more about the exciting new supplier relationship with <a href="https://www.mightypeacecoffee.com/" target="_blank" title="Mighty Peace Coffee" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mighty Peace Coffee</a>! </p>
<p><strong>Mighty Peace Coffee</strong> is a fully integrated social impact coffee company that provides coffee lovers and ethical businesses with the highest quality coffee from the Democratic Republic of Congo (DRC). Mighty Peace Coffee shares stories of Congolese farmers to inspire human connection, breaking the cycle of poverty and conflict through economic transformation and advocacy. They like to call this style of business, "Peace Trade Coffee."</p>
<h3>Pillars of the Peace Trade</h3>
<ol>
<li>Environmental sustainability and organic certification</li>
<li>Highest labor standards, fair trade, and fair trade-equivalent certifications</li>
<li>Partnerships with credible organizations working to create an economic transformation in conflict coffee-growing regions</li>
</ol>
<h3>Impact</h3>
<p>Each new arrival from Mighty Peace Coffee supports 600 jobs. The coffee business is enabling multiple stakeholders to earn a better living, build cement houses, enroll their children in school and provide healthcare for their families.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/8KRdNvDLJnA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<h3>A Farmer’s Story</h3>
<p style="float: right;"><img alt="Photo of Mrs. Katambara Pendeza Apoline" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Katambara-Pendeza-Apoline.png?v=1582391541" style="margin-left: 5px; float: right;">Mrs. Katambara Pendeza Apoline is a dignified farmer who grows coffee for Mighty Peace Coffee. As a result of our work together, she is able to send her children to school to study and she has been able to build a strong stable house for her and her family to live. She is part of a strong vibrant community of farmers whose collective action provides economic and financial stability for a better life for her, her family and community.</p>
<h3>Get Peace Trade Coffee now!</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee/products/rise-up-peace-island-congolese-coffee" alt="Rise Up, Peace Island - Peace Trade Coffee from DR Congo"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/RSR-Bag-DRC-PeaceIsland-12OZ_large.jpg?v=1578866975" alt="Rise Up, Peace Island product photo"><br><em>Rise Up, Peace Island - Apple &amp; Citrus, Heavy Body, Sweet</em></a></p>
<h3>Existing Presence</h3>
<p>Ross Street Roasting is the first Iowa based roaster to offer Mighty Peace Coffee. In addition to Iowa, Mighty Peace Coffee is currently available from roasters in Alaska, Connecticut, Colorado, Illinois, Indiana, Michigan, Missouri, New York, Oregon, Pennsylvania, and Wisconsin.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/new-monkey-on-the-block-the-howling-monkey</id>
    <published>2020-01-12T22:03:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-01-12T22:04:58-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/new-monkey-on-the-block-the-howling-monkey"/>
    <title>New Monkey on the Block: The Howling Monkey</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian goes behind the scenes on our new barrel-aged coffee: The Howling Monkey<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/new-monkey-on-the-block-the-howling-monkey">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Many Ross Street Roasting fans are familiar with our whiskey barrel-aged Ethiopian coffee, The Stumbling Monkey. But just today we released what might be called a sibling coffee: <a alt="The Howling Monkey" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee/products/the-howling-monkey-tequila-barrel-aged-nicaraguan-coffee">The <em>Howling</em> Monkey</a> - A tequila barrel-aged Nicaraguan coffee, using direct relationship coffee from our pals at Gold Mountain Coffee Growers in Nicaragua. New spirit, new barrel, new monkey. You might say we're starting 2020 with a howl and a swing through the trees. </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/dimitry-b-3GsHYJFe-qI-unsplash_medium.jpg?v=1578888278" alt="Black Howler Monkey"></p>
<p>Howling Monkeys (or Howler Monkeys) are native to Central America, including Nicaragua. As I was cooking up the plans for this new barrel-aged coffee, I was chatting on WhatsApp with the Founder/CEO of <a href="https://www.goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com/" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - Direct Trade Nicaraguan Specialty Coffee" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</a>, Benjamin Weiner. It was Ben who originally made the suggestion to call this new coffee by the Spanish name for these animals: Mono Congo. </p>
<p>When he suggested this, it fired a connection to a memory from our first trip to Nicaragua in 2018. My wife, daughter, and I had come down together and spent a few days in the coffeelands with Ben and the Gold Mountain crew before heading down to the Pacific coast to the resort town of San Juan del Sur. We had rented a cabin north of the town in a gated community just a 1/2 mile walk to the beach. Trees covered the entire neighborhood.</p>
<p>Our first night at the cabin, my wife and I were woken up in the middle of the night by strange scuffling sounds on the roof of our cabin. We froze, lying in bed, staring up at the vaulted ceiling above us, feeling helpless and terrified. We had no idea what was going on. So we waited.</p>
<p>And the scuffling sounds just kept going and going and going.</p>
<p>After a few hours, the fear started to wear off but we were still just completely confused as to what was going on atop the roof of our cabin. So as dawn began to break, I finally had a chance to peek out the windows. It was too dark to tell, but I could barely see a number of black shapes shuffling through the trees above the cabin. Apparently whatever was up there was also crawling on the roof of the cabin.</p>
<p>Finally, the sun had risen enough to shed more light on the situation and the mystery was solved: There was a pack of black howler monkeys migrating from one spot to another through the night and into the morning, and apparently our cabin was on the monkey highway.</p>
<p>So...naturally, I went outside and tried to talk to them...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z8CFHqxuyGc" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p>There you have it, folks: The origin story for our new seasonal release, The Howling Monkey. (Read <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-stumbling-monkey-his-story" title="The Stumbling Monkey: His story">The Stumbling Monkey's story</a> here)</p>
<p><em>Awesome Black Howler Monkey photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@dimitry_b?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Dimitry B</a> via <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/howler-monkey?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/advice-for-rural-entrepreneurs</id>
    <published>2019-12-31T09:32:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-31T09:32:51-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/advice-for-rural-entrepreneurs"/>
    <title>Advice for rural entrepreneurs</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian summarizes lessons learned from starting a business in a rural area, from a piece posted at a new online resource for rural entrepreneurialism, the <a href="https://www.rusticentrepreneur.com/" target="_blank" title="The Rustic Entrepreneur - online authority and community of entrepreneurs, business owners, students, and academics who work in or were raised in rural/suburban America and have a passion for entrepreneurship" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rustic Entrepreneur</a>.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/advice-for-rural-entrepreneurs">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Business happens on social media, and not just retail businesses like ours reaching customers. For instance, our first green coffee supplier relationship, a direct relationship with <a href="https://www.goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com/" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - High-cupping specialty coffee from Nicaragua" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</a> in Nicaragua, started on Instagram.</p>
<p>And within the last week, we noticed a new follow notification from an awesome new resource for rural entrepreneurs: <a href="https://www.rusticentrepreneur.com/" target="_blank" title="Rustic Entrepreneur - Online resource and community for rural entrepreneurship " rel="noopener noreferrer">The Rustic Entrepreneur</a>, "an online authority and community of entrepreneurs, business owners, students, and academics who work in or were raised in rural/suburban America and have a passion for entrepreneurship." </p>
<p>The site organizer, Grady Connolly, reached out to me and asked if I'd help contribute some of the first content to their blog and I happily agreed. So check out the results of that here: </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.rusticentrepreneur.com/post/ross-street-roasting-co" target="_blank" title="Rustic Entrepreneur Spotlight: Ross Street Roasting Co." rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Rustic Entrepreneur Spotlight: Ross Street Roasting Co.<br>Turning coffee drinkers into coffee lovers</strong></a></p>
<p>At the end of the piece, I offer a few points of advice for entrepreneurs thinking of starting businesses in rural areas:</p>
<ul>
<li>If you're considering retail: Be realistic about the state of local brick &amp; mortar retail in rural areas (Hint: It ain't pretty)</li>
<li>Leverage the internet as much as possible, to get you the largest possible customer base</li>
<li>Be active and engaging on social media, particularly Facebook</li>
<li>Network with entrepreneur communities in your nearest city (I've participated in the <a href="https://www.1millioncups.com/" target="_blank" title="1 Million Cups - Caffeinating an entrepreneurial nation" rel="noopener noreferrer">1 Million Cups</a> communities in Cedar Rapids &amp; Des Moines, and that's a nationwide network)</li>
<li>Hire a bookkeeper/accountant sooner rather than later (I learned this the hard way)</li>
<li>Set measurable &amp; realistic goals and hold yourself accountable to them somehow (I have investor-partners, so accountability is necessary for me).</li>
</ul>
<p>Anything else you'd recommend or correct me on? </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-steps-to-brewing-better-coffee</id>
    <published>2019-11-30T16:49:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2019-11-30T17:20:28-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-steps-to-brewing-better-coffee"/>
    <title>3 Steps to Brewing Better Coffee</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian summarizes 3 simple steps to improving your home coffee brewing game.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-steps-to-brewing-better-coffee">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Hi coffee friends! - Of all the things I've learned about brewing a better cup of coffee over the years, it really boils down to three simple things:</p>
<ol>
<li>Coffee</li>
<li>Grinder</li>
<li>Water</li>
</ol>
<p>If you can cover these 3 bases, your cup of coffee in the morning can be consistently awesome - regardless of your brewing method/device. Below, I'll break down each one and why they're so important.</p>
<h2>1. Coffee - Get it Fresh, pay for Quality</h2>
<p>If you want an awesome cup of coffee, you have to start with awesome roasted coffee. Coffee is an incredibly diverse, complex beverage. In fact, there are more potential flavors in coffee than you'll find in wine. And like most food and beverage, there are quality grades to coffee. Some is terrible and cheap. Some is incredible and costly. And there's a lot of in-between.</p>
<p>Two things to keep in mind with awesome coffee: a) buy Specialty-grade; and b) buy it from a roaster that sells <em>then</em> roasts (not the other way around). Many roasters around the country follow this "roast to order" model and source only Specialty Coffee, and we're one.  Check out our offerings:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee" title="Single Origin Coffees">Single Origin Coffees</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/gourmet-coffee-blends" title="Gourmet Coffee Blends">Gourmet Coffee Blends</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/80-acre-espresso" title="80-Acre Espresso series">80-Acre Espresso series</a></li>
</ul>
<h2>2. Grinder - Buy Whole Bean, Grind per batch</h2>
<p>Coffee goes stale when exposed to oxygen. <em>Whole Bean</em> coffee stays "fresh" about 2-4 weeks after its roast date. After that, even a well-sealed bag, oxygen will start to rob some of the flavors of any coffee, even the good stuff. Read more: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/specialty-coffee-freshness-prolonging-the-magic" title="Specialty Coffee &amp; Freshness: Prolonging the Magic">Specialty Coffee &amp; Freshness - Prolonging the Magic</a></p>
<p>The next question is: Which grinder do I need? First: Get a burr grinder. They're <em>far</em> superior to blade grinders. There are many burr grinders to choose from, and we have this handy blog post to help you figure out what will work best for your situation: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/choosing-the-right-coffee-grinder-for-your-home" title="Choosing the right coffee grinder for your home">Choosing the Right Coffee Grinder for your Home</a> - And check out the 2 that we offer:</p>
<ul>
<li>Manual: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/handground-grinder" title="Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder">Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder</a>
</li>
<li>Electric: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/baratza-encore-electric-conical-burr-grinder" title="Baratza Encore - Electric Conical Burr Grinder">Baratza Encore - Electric Conical Burr Grinder</a>
</li>
</ul>
<h2>3. Water - The Unsung Hero</h2>
<p>A cup of coffee is 98% water. If you use terrible water, you'll make even the best Specialty Coffee taste like a cup full of "meh." So check out our handy guide to improving your water situation for brewing coffee: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/is-bad-water-ruining-your-coffee-heres-how-to-fix-it" title="Is bad water ruining your coffee? Here's how to fix it">Is bad water ruining your coffee? Here's how to fix it</a></p>
<p>And check out this awesome coffee water hack: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/third-wave-water-12-one-gallon-sticks-classic-profile" title="Third Wave Water">Third Wave Water</a></p>
<p>So there you have it: 3 simple steps to brewing better coffee at home. Happy brewing, coffee friends! </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-use-a-scale-for-brewing-coffee</id>
    <published>2019-11-26T13:24:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-12-01T08:47:19-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-use-a-scale-for-brewing-coffee"/>
    <title>How To Use a Scale for Brewing Coffee</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian explains why using mass (weight) rather than volume can help improve your home coffee brewing.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-use-a-scale-for-brewing-coffee">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>About a year before becoming a coffee roaster, I started improving aspects of my home coffee <em>brewing</em> game. First, it was buying better coffee (Specialty-grade, fresh-roasted, from roasters like us ;) ). Then came <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/choosing-the-right-coffee-grinder-for-your-home" title="Choosing the right coffee grinder for your home">a better grinder</a>.</p>
<p>The improvement I'll focus on in this post is <strong>the use of a scale</strong> for weighing out coffee and water prior to brewing. This method stands in contrast to the common use of some kind of scoop just for coffee grounds. My argument is that the use of a scale is the superior approach. First I'll explain <em>why</em>, then <em>how</em> you can make this transition. </p>
<h2>Why use a Scale?</h2>
<p>Why is using a scale to weigh out coffee and water important? It comes down to one thing: <strong>Consistency.</strong></p>
<p>By using a scale, you can establish what's known as a "brewing ratio." For making <strong>drip coffee</strong> at home in something like <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/aeropress-single-serve-manual-brewer" title="AeroPress Single-Serve Manual Brewer">the AeroPress</a>, another pour-over device, or even an electric coffee maker - common ratios of coffee to water are in the 1:17 range. Doing this will directly correlate to how "strong" your cup of coffee is, and you can tweak your ratio depending on brewing device, whether or not you're adding milk or sugar, and personal preference. </p>
<h2>Putting it into Practice</h2>
<p>So what does this look like in practice? Well, first of all, you're going to need a kitchen scale, preferably one that also has a timer function. (We just so happen to sell <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/smart-brew-coffee-scale-with-timer-rsr-logo" title="Smart Brew Coffee Scale with Timer &amp; RSR Logo">an awesome one</a> with the RSR logo etched on the surface!) The unit commonly used for weights &amp; ratios in coffee brewing is <em><strong>grams</strong></em>.</p>
<h3>Example: The 10oz "Quick Morning Cup"</h3>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/foXZbRCaaQ8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<ul>
<li>Desired output: 10oz cup</li>
<li>Water required: <strong>284 gr</strong> (10oz converted to grams)</li>
<li>Coffee required: <strong>16.7 gr</strong> (284 divided by 17)</li>
<li>Brewing device/method: AeroPress (traditional method)</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Pro tip: Use the "cheat sheet" at the bottom of this post to save yourself from constant unit conversions on your phone.</em></p>
<ol>
<li>Weight out <strong>16.7 gr</strong> of coffee beans &amp; grind them (medium-fine for the AeroPress)</li>
<li>Put the grounds into the AeroPress</li>
<li>Place your mug with the bottom half of the AeroPress onto the scale</li>
<li>Tare the scale (zero it out)</li>
<li>Start the timer and begin adding water (approx 200ºF) until it reaches <strong>284 gr</strong>
</li>
<li>Stir the water/grounds slurry for 3-5 seconds</li>
<li>Steep water/grounds slurry for another 45-60 seconds</li>
<li>Remove the mug+AeroPress from the scale</li>
<li>Finish the brew by plunging out the contents of AeroPress into the cup</li>
<li>Enjoy</li>
</ol>
<p>Total brew time with pouring, stirring, steeping, &amp; plunging: ~90 seconds.</p>
<p><em>Note: Some AeroPress nerds will howl at this and suggest other/better brewing methods, and that's fine. Go to YouTube for those instructional videos. This post is about the scale. :) </em></p>
<p>People who are coming from electric brewing methods or pods machines often see me going to all this work to make a single cup of coffee and scoff. I get it. It takes time and effort. </p>
<p>But here's the thing: Like most work, practice makes perfect. And the "new" work eventually becomes second nature/muscle memory. So after 5+ years of brewing this way on various devices (AeroPress, Chemex, Kalita Wave, etc.) - I hardly even think about it anymore. </p>
<p>So if you care about making a great cup of coffee and are willing to work a bit at it at first, you'll eventually become a killer cup-brewing machine and not have to fuss too much about it.</p>
<p>And you'll also be able to take this ratio to any number of other brewing devices and methods. Keep in mind that the 1:17 ratio is specifically for <em>drip coffee</em>. Other devices/methods use other ratios. Espresso is usually about 1:2. Cold brew concentrate is about 1:3.</p>
<p>So there you have it: The Why &amp; How of using a scale for brewing coffee. Enjoy your knowledge upgrade, coffee lovers!</p>
<h2>Resource: Brew Ratio Cheat Sheet</h2>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Home_Coffee_Brewing_Numbers_-_Google_Sheets.png?v=1574793465" alt="1:17 Coffee Brewing Ratio Cheat Sheet" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>Of course, feel free to make your own cheat sheet based on your preferred ratio.</p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/choosing-the-right-coffee-grinder-for-your-home</id>
    <published>2019-11-13T15:47:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2020-12-01T08:47:13-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/choosing-the-right-coffee-grinder-for-your-home"/>
    <title>Choosing the right Coffee Grinder for your Home</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian breaks down the factors that go into choosing the right type of coffee grinder for your home coffee making situation.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/choosing-the-right-coffee-grinder-for-your-home">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>There's no way around it: Pre-ground coffee goes stale...<em>fast</em>. And we get it: Sometimes you just don't want to jack around with grinding coffee in the morning if you're in a hurry.</p>
<p>But if you want to keep your Awesome Coffee from us fresh as long as possible: Get a coffee grinder, and order your coffee Whole Bean. It's that simple. But <em>which</em> grinder should you get? That can be a bit more complicated...</p>
<p>In this guide we'll walk you through the considerations for making the best decision when it comes to buying a coffee grinder for your situation.</p>
<h2>Ground or Pulverized?</h2>
<p>The first thing to know is that there are 2 main types of home coffee grinders you'll find in the market:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<strong>Blade Grinders</strong> - Think "mini food processor." It's got an on/off button and a set of blades inside the grinding chamber. Beans go in. Button goes down. Blades go 'round and 'round. Beans gets chopped up. Simple. </li>
<li>
<strong>Burr Grinders</strong> - Think "spice mill." These grinders have granularity settings (coarse, medium, fine), and use steel or ceramic grinding burrs to grind, rather than pulverize, the beans.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Simple advice: Go for #2</h3>
<p>With blade grinders you have absolutely no way to control grind settings, and you always end up with wildly inconsistent grind particle sizes, which makes for wildly inconsistent brews. And like with most things in Specialty Coffee: Quality &amp; Consistency is king. </p>
<p>The 2 advantages that burr grinders have are</p>
<ol>
<li>Their ability to change the grind size</li>
<li>Their ability to grind consistently </li>
</ol>
<p>Blade grinders can do neither, and advantage #1 is crucial if you're using different brewing methods at home. With the advent of Cold Brew Coffee and its growing popularity with coffee drinkers, many cold brew lovers have started thinking, "Can I make this at home?" <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/cold-brew-coffee-maker-with-flip-cap-lid-2-quart" title="Cold Brew Coffee Maker with Flip Lid - 2 Quart">The answer is Yes</a>, but you'll need a grinder that can do a coarse grind. And your regular coffee maker is going to use more of a medium grind. And the AeroPress or a Moka Pot needs a bit finer grind. Etc.</p>
<p>You'll need a grinder that can adjust to your brew methods at home, and only burr grinders can do that.</p>
<h2>Advantage: Burr Grinders</h2>
<p>Hopefully I've convinced you that burr grinders are the way to go. But now the question remains: <em>Which </em>burr grinder? There are plenty on the market, and we happen to sell 2 that we think are both great options in specific situations. One is manual, the other is electric. I'll discuss each type and their benefits...</p>
<h3>Option 1: The Handground - A Manual Precision Burr Grinder</h3>
<p style="float: right;"><img alt="Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/handground-black_ac657755-0479-4998-98e4-0d9454846620_compact.jpg?v=1561571878" style="float: right; margin-left: 5px;">What started as a Kickstarter project turned into a globe-spanning collaborative product development project, and Roaster Brian was an early backer on Kickstarter and eventually was involved (in a very small way) in the development process. The concept is simple: It's a burr grinder that you operate manually. </p>
<h4>Pros</h4>
<ul>
<li>The less expensive option</li>
<li>Smaller size - Easy to put in a cupboard or pack for travel</li>
<li>Ideal for 1-2 coffee drinkers drinking 1-2 cups of coffee per day, with manual brewing devices such as the <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/aeropress-single-serve-manual-brewer" title="AeroPress - Single-Serving Manual Coffee Brewer">AeroPress</a>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cons</h4>
<ul>
<li>Can become tiring for your arms!</li>
<li>
<em>Not</em> ideal for larger batch brewers (like an electric coffee maker)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/handground-grinder" title="Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder"><em><strong>Shop now: The Handground ($79)</strong></em></a></p>
<h3>Option 2: The Baratza Encore - Give your arms a rest, brew more coffee</h3>
<p style="float: right;"><img alt="Baratza Encore - Electric Conical Burr Grinder" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/baratza-encore-1_compact.jpg?v=1573672348" style="float: right; margin-left: 5px;">Baratza is a rock solid brand in the world of home coffee grinders. There are cheaper burr grinders out there on the market, but none can hold a candle to the build quality of its products and customer service that Baratza provides. And the Encore model has long been considered the best entry-level burr grinder on the market, which is why we carry it. Only the best for our Home Coffee Pros! </p>
<h4>Pros</h4>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<ul>
<li>You don't have to grind by hand!</li>
<li>Top-mounted hopper holds nearly a 12oz bag's worth of beans</li>
<li>Ideal for bigger brewing batches, like coffee makers and cold brew</li>
<li>Fantastic warranty and service from Baratza</li>
</ul>
<h4>Cons</h4>
<ul>
<li>Cost - Not everyone has $140 to throw around for a coffee grinder</li>
<li>
<em>(Maybe a con)</em> Bigger footprint means it has to sit out on the countertop, which might turn off some folks</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/baratza-encore-electric-conical-burr-grinder" title="Baratza Encore - Electric Conical Burr Grinder"><em><strong>Shop now: The Baratza Encore ($140)</strong></em></a></p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>So depending on how much coffee you brew, and how hard you want to work your arms - we have 2 great options to take your home coffee making operation to the next level, if you've never had a grinder or have only used the inferior blade-type grinders in the past.</p>
<p>Happy grinding, and Happy brewing, coffee friends! </p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><em>Featured image photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@wadeaustinellis?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Wade Austin Ellis</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/coffee-ground?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/is-bad-water-ruining-your-coffee-heres-how-to-fix-it</id>
    <published>2019-10-25T08:52:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-25T09:01:02-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/is-bad-water-ruining-your-coffee-heres-how-to-fix-it"/>
    <title>Is bad water ruining your coffee? Here&apos;s how to fix it</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian discusses the importance of water quality in coffee brewing, and introduces Third Wave Water as a quick and easy solution to bad water ruining Good Coffee.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/is-bad-water-ruining-your-coffee-heres-how-to-fix-it">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>As coffee lovers, we're all on a journey. And with each turn in the road, we have the opportunity to learn something new about this wonderful beverage. I clearly remember the day I started thinking about the <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>water</strong></span> I was using to brew coffee at home. I think like most people, it just hadn't ever occurred to me as something worth thinking about. But let me jump ahead and say: It is important. Very important.</p>
<p><strong>That magical cup of brown go-juice we drink is about 98% water</strong>, which means only about 2% is actual "coffee." What's in that 2% is most certainly important; heck, our entire business model is staked on that 2%.</p>
<p>But then again: 98% is water. So it stands to reason that the quality of that 98% is important.</p>
<h3>I was a Third Wave Water skeptic</h3>
<p>A few years ago, coffee twitter started chattering about this new product called "<a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/third-wave-water-12-one-gallon-sticks-classic-profile" title="Third Wave Water: 12 One Gallon Sticks - Ross Street Roasting Co.">Third Wave Water</a>," a mineral compound that added to a jug of distilled or reverse osmosis-filtered water that claimed to make your coffee taste much better. My initial thought was: "Gimme a break."</p>
<p>But then I heard the founders interviewed on a coffee podcast and I quickly realized that my skepticism was misplaced. These guys knew what they were doing, had developed it and tested it in a real-world cafe, and were "nerdy coffee types" like me. I had to try it, and when I did: I immediately signed up as a reseller.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/UKdP4yw32-c" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><strong>Shop now: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/third-wave-water-12-one-gallon-sticks-classic-profile" title="Third Wave Water: 12 One Gallon Sticks, Classic Profile">Third Wave Water- 12 One Gallon Sticks, Classic Profile</a></strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img src="https://cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/TWW_Infographic_large.png?v=1560446038" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>Third Wave Water is drop-dead simple: Add a stick of it to a jug of distilled or RO water. Use that water to make coffee. You've instantly and economically solved the problems that often come with using unfiltered, untreated municipal water for brewing coffee at home. </p>
<p style="text-align: left;">Your coffee will taste better, and you'll be happier with your morning cup. Bad water solved. You're welcome.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/bad-church-coffee-2-steps-toward-making-it-good</id>
    <published>2019-10-22T08:45:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-22T14:00:33-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/bad-church-coffee-2-steps-toward-making-it-good"/>
    <title>Bad Church Coffee: 2 Steps Toward Making it Good</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian outs himself as a church minister and talks about how to make coffee better in worshiping communities.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/bad-church-coffee-2-steps-toward-making-it-good">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Businesses aren't supposed to talk about religion, are they? Well, I'm going to break that rule and talk about something I know all too well...</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">Bad Church Coffee</h2>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y4u_SEcSj3I" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p>I'll say right up front: I grew up in the church, claimed the Christian faith as my own as an adolescent, and have been struggling to make sense of what that actually means in practice ever since. In fact, I struggled mightily enough to go and get an advanced seminary degree and get ordained as a minister. And while I'm not currently active in any formal church ministry roles, it is true that I've brought my ministerial ethics and mindset to how I conduct myself as a businessperson. </p>
<p>And I know from years of experience that coffee at church is</p>
<ol>
<li>Ubiquitous; and</li>
<li>Often terrible</li>
</ol>
<p>I've had a Jewish friend of mine tell me the same is often true in synagogues. So, people of the book: What is wrong with this picture? </p>
<p>Here's a quick theological formulation about coffee:</p>
<ul>
<li>Coffee is grown, processed, and roasted <strong>by human beings</strong>
</li>
<li>Coffee is produced <strong>by the good earth</strong> (understood as a gift that we did not create)</li>
<li>In the Christian tradition, God cares about humans caring for one another <em>and</em> for humans taking care of the earth</li>
</ul>
<p>Therefore, coffee at church is something that people of faith can and perhaps should consider sourcing and serving in a more faith-informed manner than is common.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Bad_Church_coffee_-_Square_large.png?v=1571751768" alt="2 Steps Toward Making Bad Church Coffee Good"></p>
<h2>1. Source Specialty Coffee</h2>
<p>"Specialty Coffee" isn't meaningless marketing speak. It's an internationally agreed-upon set of quality standards across the supply chain that mark out the highest quality tiers of coffee grown anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>And producers that can meet these growing and processing standards get paid far more than commodity-grade coffees that are governed by non-human market forces that too often harm coffee-growing families and communities. These producers are also very often practicing sustainable agriculture in their coffee production, making good on the call to care for the land that produces this wondrous drink so many of us love.</p>
<p>So buying higher-grade Specialty Coffee not only gets you coffee that objectively tastes better than cheap, crappy coffee - it also provides coffee growing families and communities with more income for a better standard of living. You're helping people live better lives in areas that are very often poor.</p>
<p><em>Hint: We only source Specialty Coffee.</em></p>
<h2>2. Source From Roasters With Direct Relationships</h2>
<p>If your faith community sources their coffee from a small roaster that works directly with coffee producers, your community has a more direct relationship to the source of your coffee. And that can open up some interesting opportunities for all involved. </p>
<h3>Material Aid</h3>
<p>When we've traveled to our direct relationship partner in Nicaragua, Gold Mountain Coffee Growers, we've always been encouraged to bring extra clothing that we're willing to give away. Or help fund social projects like computer classes for girls from rural mountain communities, to give them a chance at a better life with some 21st century skills. Faith communities with a relationship to their coffee producers can help in these ways.</p>
<h3>Cultural Exchange and/or Work Trips</h3>
<p>Again, to use or connection with Gold Mountain Coffee Growers in Nicaragua, the rural communities up in the mountains that grow awesome coffee that we Americans enjoy are always facing challenges on many fronts: Roads are rough and often in need of upkeep and repair. Electricity is not a given for everyone. Indoor plumbing is scarce. Houses containing large families are often in sore need of improvements or repairs. </p>
<p>Faith communities in the US with means and skilled members can assemble teams for trips to the communities where their coffee is grown, and lend a hand in improving living conditions in those communities. They'll also get to see some gorgeous landscapes and meet wonderful people while doing good work.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Finca Idealista - Matagalpa, Nicaragua" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/finca-idealista-vista_1919x800_cc300d2d-ed35-49fe-8923-b2ae029bdcd6_grande.jpg?v=1546359381" style="float: none;"><br>(Finca Idealista - Matagalpa, Nicaragua)</p>
<p><em>Hint: Over 50% of our coffee is sourced through direct relationships with producers.</em></p>
<p>So there you have it: 2 steps toward making coffee in your community of faith better, on multiple fronts. Better coffee, better livelihoods for your coffee-growing neighbors around the globe.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p><em>"Love Your Neighbour" photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@ninastrehl?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Nina Strehl</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/s/photos/church?utm_source=unsplash&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_content=creditCopyText">Unsplash</a></em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-make-awesome-campfire-coffee-with-the-aeropress</id>
    <published>2019-09-23T15:41:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-12-01T08:47:07-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-make-awesome-campfire-coffee-with-the-aeropress"/>
    <title>How to make awesome campfire coffee with the AeroPress</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian shows you how to make awesome coffee at your campsite. Whether you're RV'ing or backwoods hiking, you can make awesome coffee while you're away from the comforts of home (and your home coffee making kit).<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-to-make-awesome-campfire-coffee-with-the-aeropress">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>My wife and I have been outdoor enthusiasts since our childhood. Both of our families tent camped when we were kids, and right after we got married (20 yrs ago!) we honeymooned on the North Shore of Minnesota, along Lake Superior, and we camped and hiked at Gooseberry Falls State Park.</p>
<p>What we didn't have then, but I wish we had, was a simple and powerful tool for making awesome coffee when you're away from home doing things like camping and hiking. Or even just staying in a hotel where you <em>know</em> the coffee is going to be just terrible. I'm talking about <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/aeropress-single-serve-manual-brewer" title="AeroPress - Single-Serve Manual Brewer">the humble AeroPress</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/aeropress-devilstower_large.jpg?v=1569271155" alt="AeroPressing at Devil's Tower, Wyoming" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><em>(AeroPressing at Devil's Tower, Wyoming - Inverted method)</em></p>
<p>The AeroPress was what unseated the French Press in my home coffee making kit after a decade of brewing coffee manually. There are a few benefits of the AeroPress over the French Press:</p>
<ul>
<li>Quicker brewing times</li>
<li>Less "grit" in your cup (better filtration)</li>
<li>Easier cleanup</li>
<li>It's plastic: It travels well and won't break</li>
</ul>
<p>The French Press never left my house because it was big and made of glass. But once I got my first AeroPress, I immediately grasped the fact that I wouldn't have to be out on the road and put myself at the mercy of whatever probably terrible coffee I would encounter.</p>
<p>This guide is specific to the camping/hiking applications of brewing with an AeroPress, so I'll quickly list out the other things you'll need to pull it off:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<strong>Coffee</strong> (of course) - Pre-ground or Whole Bean</li>
<li>
<strong><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/handground-grinder" title="Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder">Hand grinder</a></strong> (optional) - If you're trying to be as lightweight and efficient as possible, you might just want to pre-ground the coffee you'll be brewing with on your trip and leave this home. But if you can pack it in, it's fun to grind your beans right before brewing at camp.</li>
<li>
<strong>Hot Water</strong> - We've used backpacking stoves for years, and recently upgraded to the <a href="https://jetboil.johnsonoutdoors.com/stoves-systems/minimo-cooking-system?_ga=2.26346488.414964335.1569269865-1832489254.1569269865" target="_blank" title="MiniMo Cooking System - JetBoil" rel="noopener noreferrer">MiniMo system from JetBoil</a>, and it's <em>amazing</em>. Heats water <em>super </em>fast. We also use it to cook food with, so it's better for us than their coffee-specific system.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Water safety note:</strong> Make sure you're either packing in potable water, or have a water filtration system if you're getting water from a natural source. Because I'm a nerd, we recently packed in a few pouches of water treated with <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/third-wave-water-12-one-gallon-sticks-classic-profile" title="Third Wave Water - Make better water for coffee brewing">Third Wave Water</a> for maximum awesomeness.</p>
<h3>Brewing Campfire Coffee with The AeroPress</h3>
<p>Okay, you've got everything packed, now how does this thing work? The AeroPress is a single-serving brewer, so you'll be making coffee for one person at a time, unless you're good at sharing.</p>
<ol>
<li>Put a filter in the AeroPress - With filter placed, lock the filter cap on the bottom of the brewer (filters are included in the bundle)</li>
<li>Dose out your coffee - For a "normal" cup of coffee, use 1 scoop of grounds (included in the AeroPress bundle)</li>
<li>Set the AeroPress on your coffee mug without the plunger part</li>
<li>Heat your water - Bring your water to a boil, and remove for 15-30 seconds</li>
<li>Pour hot water into AeroPress - Stir grounds and water for a few seconds with a spoon or the included stirring paddle</li>
<li>Wait about 30-60 secondd</li>
<li>Insert the plunger part into the top of the AeroPress and start exerting some pressure down on it. Not too hard, not too soft - The plunger should slowly work its way down and coffee will start being pushed into your cup</li>
</ol>
<p>Aaaaand, you're done! The total brew time including the first pour and stir doesn't have to be more than about 2 minutes. Check out the video to see it in action.</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WQuW49E0nd8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p>Make sure you follow Leave No Trace principles when disposing of the grounds and filter paper. If you're in the backwoods, it's best to pack out all your trash, and this would be included in that. </p>
<p>That's the "quick and easy" way to make AeroPress coffee at the campsite. If you're already a trained AeroPress nerd, you might be gasping in horror and wanting to suggest the advanced brewing methods such as the "Inverted" approach pictured above. That's cool if you want to nerd out. I'll get more nerdy on those brewing methods in other posts.</p>
<p>Happy campfire coffee drinking, coffee friends!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/award-winning-coffee-2-years-running</id>
    <published>2019-09-20T10:16:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-09-20T10:18:38-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/award-winning-coffee-2-years-running"/>
    <title>One Sweet Coffee: Winning Awards, 2 Years Running</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian explains why the Gold Mountain Brix Breaker coffee has won medals in roasting competitions 2 years in a row.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/award-winning-coffee-2-years-running">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>This week we were pleased to discover that we'd again medaled in the annual Golden Bean North America roasters competition, the 2nd year in a row. And both years we've used the same coffee: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee/products/nicaragua-gold-mountain-brix-breaker-pacamara-natural" title="Gold Mountain Brix Breaker"><strong>The Gold Mountain Brix Breaker</strong></a> - A 3-farm micro-lot from our direct relationship sourcing partners in Nicaragua, Gold Mountain Coffee Growers.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/x5LGMqUoTeE" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p>"Brix" is a weird word that requires some explanation. The Brix Scale uses refractometers (shown in the video above) to measure sugar content in a liquid.  Gold Mountain staffers use refractometers and Brix measurements during harvest to ensure that all coffees are being picked at peak ripeness. The ripest cherries will exhibit the highest level of sweetness. </p>
<p>This coffee is called the "Brix Breaker" because of its unusually high sugar content. This is a result of the tree variety used: Pacamara. There are many different varietals under the <em>Coffea Arabica</em> species, that are all considered to be "the good stuff" when it comes to commercially producing coffee plants. The Pacamara variety grows unusually large cherries with naturally high levels of sugar content. Picked at peak ripeness, the whole cherries are then sun-dried on raised beds. This "natural"/"dry" processing method further accentuates fruit notes and sweetness.</p>
<p>And once the coffee reaches us, we employ a light roast profile on it that best showcases the stunning sweetness and flavors you'll experience with this coffee.</p>
<p>So from start to finish, this coffee is treated specifically to maximize sweetness and fruitiness. It truly is a "Brix Breaker," and it's a big reason why we're able to keep winning awards with it. </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origin-coffee/products/nicaragua-gold-mountain-brix-breaker-pacamara-natural" title="Gold Mountain Brix Breaker- Direct Trade Nicaraguan Light Roast Coffee"><strong>Buy Now!</strong><br><img alt="Gold Mountain Brix Breaker" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/brix-breaker-award_large.png?v=1568992529" style="float: none;"></a></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-many-cups-of-coffee-does-a-bag-make</id>
    <published>2019-09-12T13:21:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-09-12T14:33:01-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-many-cups-of-coffee-does-a-bag-make"/>
    <title>How many cups of coffee does a bag make?</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian explains how to figure out how many cups of coffee a bag of roasted beans will produce. And then make things confusing for the sake of education and growth. Oh also: A gif.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/how-many-cups-of-coffee-does-a-bag-make">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>We get asked this somewhat regularly, and we understand why. People want to know how much coffee they're going to get out of the bags they're turning over their hard-earned money for. What's their coffee bang per precious buck? </p>
<p>Well, here's a little bit of help in that regard! In this post we'll give you some basic guidelines for how to figure this out yourself. </p>
<p>Based on the standard bag sizes we offer here at Ross Street Roasting, you can expect to get about this many cups of coffee out of each bag...</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/bag-brewing-guide_a77dc0f8-39fa-488c-b8fa-da13fdbb0c87.png?v=1568309038" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>We're making a few assumptions here, so let's just tell you what those are. This guide assumes...</p>
<ul>
<li>A 1:17 ratio of ground coffee to water used when brewing (achievable with the use of a scale)</li>
<li>A mug size of 10oz</li>
<li>Each person is only drinking 1 cup / day</li>
</ul>
<p>Things can get confusing fast in the world of brewing coffee at home. There are so many different home coffee makers out there today: Drip coffeemakers (Ye Olde Mr. Coffee), Keurigs, Nespresso's, Ninja's, French Presses, Moka pots, <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/aeropress-single-serve-manual-brewer" title="AeroPress - Single serve coffee brewer">AeroPresses</a>, and on and on and on!</p>
<p>Further complicating things is how much ground coffee to use in each device, because each type will call for differing amounts of ground coffee. (And don't even get me started on different grinds per device! - That will be another blog post.)</p>
<p>And notice above that I mentioned using ratios, weights, and a scale. I know what you're thinking...</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/aint-nobody-got-time-for-that.gif?v=1568311294" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>There are some times when even Roaster Brian ain't got time for that, either! So here's what I usually tell people when they ask "how much"...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><strong>"Just use as much ground coffee as you normally use."</strong></em></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em></em>If our coffee comes out tasting stronger than you're used to using the same amount of grounds, and you <em>like</em> that stronger flavor: Keep on keepin' on! If you <em>don't</em> like how strong it came out tasting, just use a bit less ground coffee next time.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">Interlude: The "I like a <em>bold</em> coffee" drinker</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">We get this quite often. What I've learned when coffee drinkers here in Iowa use the word "bold," what that usually means is they like dark, smoky roasts (<a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/gourmet-coffee-blends/products/bohemian-gothic-dark-roast-blend" title="Bohemian Gothic - Dark roast gourmet coffee blend">and we've got a coffee for that</a>). It's true that the acrid, bitter, smokey qualities of a dark roast seem "strong" or "bold," relative to other types of flavor notes you'll encounter in light or medium roasted coffees.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">I get it - But here's the thing: "Bold" or "strong" aren't actual flavors; they're intensity descriptors. I can make you a weaksauce cup of dark roast by using a lesser-than-normal amount of coffee grounds.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">And then I can turn around and make you a knockout punch strong cup of light roast by using a higher amount of coffee grounds in the brewing process.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/coffee-mug-in-beans.jpg?v=1568312410" alt=""></p>
<h3 style="text-align: left;">So back to the original question: How many cups?!</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;">If you love math, numbers, and spreadsheets and haven't bought yourself a scale for measuring coffee and water, you have my permission to go get one. You'll love nerding out with using mass instead of volume to measure out your coffee. And you'll get more consistent results. Use the industry standard 1:17 ratio for drip coffee as a guide, and you'll be able to calculate just how many cups of coffee you'll get out of a bag of roasted beans.</p>
<p style="text-align: left;">If you don't love math and just want the damn cup of coffee, just look back up at that handy table at the top of this post, because that's going to be a good enough place to start gauging how many cups of The Good Stuff you'll get out of our bags of fresh-roasted awesomeness. Here's an even simpler guide:</p>
<ul>
<li>5oz bag: Just under a week</li>
<li>12oz bag: About 2 weeks</li>
<li>2lb bag: About 1 month</li>
<li>5lb bag: You better have a lot of coffee drinkers in the house :) </li>
</ul>
<p>If you have any questions, critique, or want to correct the error of my ways - pipe in the comments below or sent us an email through the <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/pages/contact-us" title="RSR Contact Us page">Contact page</a>.</p>
<p>Happy brewing!</p>
<p><em>("Coffee Mug in Beans" photo by <a href="https://burst.shopify.com/@matthew_henry?utm_campaign=photo_credit&amp;utm_content=High+Res+Coffee+Mug+In+Beans+Picture+%E2%80%94+Free+Images&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=credit">Matthew Henry</a> via <a href="https://burst.shopify.com/coffee?utm_campaign=photo_credit&amp;utm_content=High+Res+Coffee+Mug+In+Beans+Picture+%E2%80%94+Free+Images&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=credit">Burst</a>)</em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/check-out-farmer-derek-milking-a-cow-for-his-moolatte</id>
    <published>2019-09-06T10:07:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-09-06T10:31:24-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/check-out-farmer-derek-milking-a-cow-for-his-moolatte"/>
    <title>Check out Farmer Derek milking a cow for his Moolatte</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Farmer Derek Klingenberg goes directly to the source for the milk in his cold brew. Literally: He holds his glass under a cow's udder and squeezes. You gotta see it for yourself.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/check-out-farmer-derek-milking-a-cow-for-his-moolatte">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Last time we checked in with our pal Farmer Derek was after <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/farmer-derek-klingenberg-goes-to-origin-for-coffee-hugs" title="Farmer Derek's trip to Nicaragua">our trip to Nicaragua in January</a>. Over the summer, he fell in love with making cold brew coffee at home (he must have read <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/making-great-cold-brew-coffee-at-home" title="Making great cold brew coffee at home">our guide</a>) and he apparently got it into his head that he needed to get the freshest milk possible for his cold brew.</p>
<p>Because he went and milked a cow directly into his cold brew. LOL - Check it out:</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/7ODdK2jqanQ" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<p> </p>
<h3>He also invents new words for coffee drinks</h3>
<p>Farmer Derek has a very creative mind, as you can see. He's also good at making up words. Like he calls cold brew coffee, "fresso" (refrigerator+espresso). Of course cold brew coffee and espresso are <em>completely</em> different brewing methods and produce dramatically different tasting coffee, but that's not gonna stop Farmer Derek, nooooo! </p>
<p>And then comes the "moolatte" (my favorite made-up term). In the video he demonstrates the recipe:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em>Fresso + Milk directly from a cow's udder = <strong>MOOLATTE</strong></em></p>
<p>Here in Iowa, I'm gonna have to look around for a few nearby dairies (like <a href="https://hansendairy.com/" target="_blank" title="Hansen's Dairy" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hansen's</a> or <a href="http://www.countryviewdairy.com/" target="_blank" title="Country View Dairy" rel="noopener noreferrer">Country View</a>) to see if I can't mix myself up a delicious Moolatte. :) </p>
<p>As Derek says at the end of the video, we're running a <strong>FREE Shipping</strong> deal on our <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/gifts-for-coffee-lovers/products/2qt-cold-brew-coffee-maker-bohemian-gothic-bundle" title="Cold brew maker + Coffee bundle">2QT Cold Brew Maker + 2LB Bohemian Gothic bundle</a>, using the promo code...you guessed it: <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>MOOLATTE</strong></span></p>
<p><em>Follow Farmer Derek: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/klingpossum" target="_blank" title="Farmer Derek on YouTube" rel="noopener noreferrer">YouTube</a> | <a href="http://instagram.com/farmerderek1" target="_blank" title="Farmer Derek on Instragram" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram</a> | <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Klingenbergstudios/" target="_blank" title="Klingenberg Farms Studios on Facebook" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook</a></em><br><em>Follow Kerry @ Keriel Dairy: <a href="http://www.kerieldairy.com/" target="_blank" title="Keriel Dairy website" rel="noopener noreferrer">Website</a> | <a href="https://www.instagram.com/imarriedamilkman/" target="_blank" title="Kerry Weibe on Instagram" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram</a> | <a href="https://www.facebook.com/KerielDairy/" target="_blank" title="Keriel Dairy on Facebook" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook</a></em></p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/cafe-partner-spotlight-brewhemia-cedar-rapids-iowa</id>
    <published>2019-08-29T14:42:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-08-29T14:45:03-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/cafe-partner-spotlight-brewhemia-cedar-rapids-iowa"/>
    <title>Café partner spotlight: Brewhemia (Cedar Rapids, Iowa)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Nestled within the New Bohemia ("NewBo") district of Cedar Rapids, Iowa, is one of the state's top tier coffee shops: <a href="https://www.brewhemia.com" target="_blank" title="Brewhemia - Specialty coffee shop in Cedar Rapids, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brewhemia</a>. Before I tell you about this wonderful shop, let's do some quick history.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://crmainstreet.org/history-of-the-district/" target="_blank" title="CRMainStreet.org - History of New Bohemia &amp; Czech Village Districts" rel="noopener noreferrer">CRMainStreet.org</a>, in the early 20th century the area now called New Bohemia was designated by the city to be a warehouse district to many large-scale manufacturing and wholesale businesses. By the late 20th century, the district had fallen on hard times and was then dealt a severe blow in 2008 when a massive flood hit Cedar Rapids, putting much of the district - and the other parts of the city near the Cedar River - underwater. In May of 2009, the city renamed the district "New Bohemia" and began pouring significant resources into recovery and economic redevelopment. In the 10 years since, NewBo has flourished into a bustling neighborhood with many retail and corporate businesses, as well as new residential living options.</p>
<p>In other words: NewBo is the <em>perfect</em> spot for a coffee shop! Enter: Brewhemia.</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/brewhemia-interior.jpg?v=1567104481" alt=""></p>
<p>Co-Founder Steve Shriver was kind enough to conduct a little interview with me over email, so read on for Brewhemia's story and how they see their role in the community, as well as some lessons learned after 6 years of helping run a top-notch café...</p>
<h4>Roaster Brian: What's the "Brewhemia startup story?"</h4>
<p>Steve Shriver: We wanted to start up a family business in the New Bohemia district so we started looking for opportunities in 2013. We decided to open an Iowa tap room specializing in Iowa craft beer. After an unsuccessful attempt to obtain a space to run the tap room we came across a little slow neighborhood coffee shop for sale. It sold Iowa beer but really specialized in Third Wave/Specialty Coffee. We decided that coffee was something we could really get excited about so we purchased it and re-branded it to Brewhemia. During the rebrand process we improved the menu and expanded the offerings. We began attracting new customers every day who became our regulars. The rest is history!</p>
<h4>RB: How do you see yourself as a member of your community/neighborhood?</h4>
<p>SS: When we launched Brewhemia we believed Cedar Rapids needed an independent, locally owned cafe that served as a hub to the community. We love to see the role we play to the hundreds of customers we have every day. We see everything from artists, entrepreneurs, families, politicians and beyond. Blue collar workers get their coffee on the way to work, a musician writes music alone in a booth while an architect shares drawings with a client and everything in between. We are proud to facilitate every one of these interactions and experiences.</p>
<h4>RB: What's been your biggest "hard lesson" learned?</h4>
<p>SS: The slow times are hard. We built the business up to handle the occasional line out the door and with that comes overhead costs. In the depths of winter when we see fewer customers than average it can be challenging. We want to be ready to provide a great experience at any moment but sometimes it's hard to predict and sometimes it's easy to overspend on labor. Managing cashflow as it relates to this is probably the toughest lesson we've learned. </p>
<h4>RB: What about owning Brewhemia brings you the most joy?</h4>
<p>SS: Knowing how many people we positively impact daily. From the growers of our coffee, our suppliers, our employees all the way through to the customers!</p>
<h4>RB: What about owning Brewhemia gives you the biggest headache?</h4>
<p>SS: Road construction. Anytime we have road construction or road closures in the neighborhood we see a dip in business. We know it's a pain for our customers and we can't do anything about it.</p>
<h3>How RSR became besties with Brewhemia</h3>
<p>Brewhemia has a near and dear place in my heart, as they played a key role in the early growth of Ross Street Roasting Co. Founded in 2015 and fully operational in the 4th quarter, we didn't start seeking out wholesale clients until early 2016. Tama-Toledo is an hour from Cedar Rapids, and is one of the closest metro markets to us. I had begun networking with the CR entrepreneurial community through the <a href="https://www.1millioncups.com/icr" title="1 Million Cups - Cedar Rapids, Iowa chapter">local chapter of 1 Million Cups</a>. I applied and was accepted to give a pitch for my new business, and the organizer was kind enough to pass me the name of Steve's wife and Brewhemia co-owner, Andrea Shriver.</p>
<p>After I dropped off some samples, the staff and owners at Brewhemia had a chance to try our coffee. I believe it was a single origin Kenyan coffee. A few days later one of the owners called back and said they'd loved the samples and were interesting in partnering with us. </p>
<p>And as Steve said above, "The rest is history!" Steve was also very generous to give us this testimonial after 3+ years of our working together: "<em>Ross Street Roasting has been a top rated supplier of Brewhemia for over 3 years. They have always delivered premium coffee, on time, and in full. As our cold brew business spikes in the summer, RSR is able to accommodate larger orders while maintaining consistency. We are proud to offer their coffee at the busiest independently owned coffee shop in Cedar Rapids!</em>" Thx, y'all! :) </p>
<p>I'm obviously biased, but I truly believe Brewhemia is something special. Their commitment to Specialty Coffee is of course important, but their food is also fantastic, the menu is impressive, and the owners and staff are awesome human beings. They also have a nice back-bar with a rotating cast of Iowa craft beers for when I stop in after "coffee drinking hours." </p>
<p>On the operations side, they take staff training seriously and we've done a few cupping events with them over the past 3 years we've worked together to boost staff knowledge on the roasting &amp; growing/production aspects of Specialty Coffee. I rely on them to be a sounding board for new coffees that we roll out, and I work my butt off to keep them happy when I hear any feedback, questions, or concerns that come back from them.</p>
<p>So if you find yourself driving through or anywhere near Cedar Rapids, stop in and say hi to my friends at Brewhemia and grab coffee and some food. They'll treat you right.</p>
<p><strong>Brewhemia</strong><br>1202 3rd St SE #101<br>Cedar Rapids, IA 52401 (<a href="https://goo.gl/maps/F97AacPm8841SjwCA" target="_blank" title="Map / directions for Brewhemia" rel="noopener noreferrer">map it</a>)<br><a href="https://www.brewhemia.com" target="_blank" title="Brewhemia - Specialty coffee shop Cedar Rapids, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">www.Brewhemia.com</a> | <a href="https://www.facebook.com/Brewhemia/" target="_blank" title="Brewhemia on Facebook" rel="noopener noreferrer">Facebook</a> | <a href="https://www.instagram.com/Brewhemia/" target="_blank" title="Brewhemia on Instragram" rel="noopener noreferrer">Instagram</a></p>
<p> </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/making-great-cold-brew-coffee-at-home</id>
    <published>2019-07-30T11:52:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-12-01T08:46:56-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/making-great-cold-brew-coffee-at-home"/>
    <title>Making Great Cold Brew Coffee at Home</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian describes the ins and outs of cold brew coffee, and how to make it at home without any fancy equipment.<meta charset="utf-8"><span> Understand cold brew and make it easily at home with our simple recipe. </span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/making-great-cold-brew-coffee-at-home">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Cold brew coffee has made a big splash in the coffee world over the past 5+ years. Once looked at with skepticism by Specialty Coffee professionals who dismissed it as a passing fad, quite the opposite has happened: Cold brew coffee just keeps gaining steam in the marketplace and shows no signs of going away. It has become a permanent fixture.</p>
<p>And it's easy for me to see why: Cold brew coffee appeals to people who normally don't drink hot coffee because of its bitterness. For me as a roaster &amp; shop owner, I've viewed cold brew coffee as a "gateway drug" to help ease people into the wonderful world of Specialty Coffee.</p>
<p>In this post, I will explain what Cold Brew coffee is and how it differs from other cold coffee drinks, and then give you a simple recipe to make cold brew concentrate at home with recommendations on which roasted coffees are well-suited for it.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Iced Cold Brew Latte" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/tyler-nix-tU97-ceagL4-unsplash_large.jpg?v=1564505388" style="margin-top: 10px; margin-bottom: 10px; float: none;"></p>
<h2>Cold Brew: What it is (and isn't)</h2>
<p>This is usually what I run into when introducing people to the idea of cold brew: When I say "cold brew," many normal coffee drinkers hear "cold coffee" and think I'm talking about coffee that was brewed hot and then made cold somehow. "Iced coffee" is something that has historically been seen on cafe menus, and it is hot-brewed coffee that's been cooled down, usually very quickly. Hot coffee drinks in their various forms can be brewed in anywhere from 30 seconds to 5 minutes.</p>
<p>Cold Brew, on the other hand, employs cold water <em>from start to finish</em>, and utilizes brewing/steeping times of 12-24 <em>hours</em>. This "low (temp) and slow (time)" brewing method produces a drink that has much lower bitterness levels than coffee brewed with hot water, but still contains the unmistakable and delightful flavors of coffee.</p>
<p>And it's precisely this lower bitterness that many people who don't normally drink coffee can easily get into drinking cold brew. Through biology and conditioning, some people just can't withstand the bitterness of hot coffee, but are capable of drinking smooth, less bitter cold brew. And there's no shame in that! </p>
<p>Note: Some claim that cold brew has lower <em>acidity</em>, but this is not the case. Acidity and bitterness are related, but distinct. Cold brew coffee has similar levels of acidity to hot coffee, but is far less bitter. Just remember: Acidity ≠ Bitterness. It is the case that some people with sensitive stomachs have an easier time with cold brew than with hot coffee. I'll leave this up to the individual to test out.</p>
<h2>Make Cold Brew at Home</h2>
<p>Another nice thing about cold brew is that it is super easy to make at home, and you don't need any fancy expensive gear to do it (though such gear does exist). Here's how I make cold brew at home using a few common kitchen items.</p>
<p>Here's what you'll need:</p>
<ul>
<li>Our <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/cofee-gear/products/cold-brew-coffee-maker-with-flip-cap-lid-2-quart" title="Cold Brew Coffee Maker w/ Flip Cap (2 Quart)">Cold Brew Maker w/ Flip Cap (2 Quart)</a>
</li>
<li>Cold, filtered water - Distilled or Reverse Osmosis yields the tastiest results</li>
<li>RSR coffee - <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/bohemian-gothic-dark-roast-blend" title="Bohemian Gothic - Dark Roast Blend 100% Direct Trade">Bohemian Gothic,</a> <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/dr-doolittles-espresso-classico-medium-dark-roast-direct-trade-espresso-blend" title="Dr. Doolittle's Espresso Classico - Medium-Dark Roast Blend 100% Direct Trade">Dr. Doolittle's Espresso</a>, &amp; <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origins/products/the-stumbling-monkey-whiskey-barrel-aged-ethiopian-coffee" title="The Stumbling Monkey - Whiskey Barrel-aged Ethiopian Coffee">Stumbling Monkey</a> are great choices</li>
<li>Optional: Coffee grinder - Check out our two models: <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/cofee-gear/products/handground-grinder" title="Handground - Precision Manual Burr Grinder">Handground/manual</a> &amp; <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/cofee-gear/products/baratza-encore-electric-canonical-burr-grinder" title="Baratza Encore - Electric Conical Burr Grinder">Baratza Encore/electric</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are the steps to make cold brew concentrate:</p>
<ol>
<li>Measure 2 Cups of coffee beans and grind them as coarsely as possible</li>
<li>Add coffee grounds into the filter and place inside the Mason jar</li>
<li>Slowly fill the rest of the jar with water, through the grounds in the filter - You can use a long spoon to help agitate the grounds to ensure they get fully saturated</li>
<li>Put the flip cap lid on the jar and place it in the refrigerator for 12-24 hours (Overnight usually works well, so you have it ready for your morning coffee!)</li>
<li>After the steeping time, remove the filter from the Mason jar and dispose of the grounds (composted coffee grounds make good dirt!)</li>
<li>Put the flip cap back on the Mason jar, and you're done!</li>
</ol>
<p><em>Wala!</em> You now have about 6 Cups of Cold Brew <em>concentrate</em>. It's concentrate, because the ratio of coffee grounds to water used was about 1:3, versus the usual 1:17 to 1:20 of the typical cup of hot drip coffee. Because of its strength, you will mostly likely want to dilute it down to "ready to drink" strength, and here are a few ways you can do that...</p>
<p>Ways to enjoy your cold brew:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<strong>Iced black cold brew</strong> - Fill a glass with ice, fill it half full of concentrate, then top off with more cold water</li>
<li>
<strong>Iced cold brew latte</strong> <em>(pictured above)</em> - Fill a glass with ice, fill it half full of concentrate, then top off with cold milk/cream or milk alternative, then stir it all up</li>
<li>
<strong>Sweeten the deal</strong> - We don't sugar shame here at RSR, so if you add some syrups and/or sugar, go for it. It's yummy! :) </li>
<li>
<strong>Iced Irish Coffee</strong> - Cold brew makes a great mixer with Irish whiskey and Bailey's! Put it on ice and top with whipped cream, and mmmmm!</li>
</ul>
<p>If you've never made cold brew at home, all this might seen like a lot of work at first. But once you've done it a few times and figured out how to work it into a schedule, starting a batch the night before and straining it out the next morning will become second nature in no time. And you'll have awesome cold brew concentrate ready to go for whatever way you'd like to enjoy it most.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> You can use the recipe above without our <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/cofee-gear/products/cold-brew-coffee-maker-with-flip-cap-lid-2-quart" title="Cold Brew Coffee Maker w/ Flip Cap (2 Quart)">cold brew maker</a>, but it does make things <em>much</em> easier. Otherwise you're fiddling around with ways to strain the coffee after the steep. But if you just use a 1:3 coffee-to-water ratio, it's still pretty easy to make cold brew at home.</p>
<p>Happy cold brewing, folks! </p>
<h3>Recommended Coffees</h3>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/bohemian-gothic-dark-roast-blend?variant=37059154832" title="Bohemian Gothic - Dark Roast Blend, 2lb bag"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/RSR-Bag-BohemianGothic-2LB_70ca7ed3-58bd-4533-985b-b29eda294a5f_medium.jpg?v=1560881767" style="float: left;"></a><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/dr-doolittles-espresso-classico-medium-dark-roast-direct-trade-espresso-blend" title="Dr. Doolittle's Espresso Classico - Medium-Dark Roast Espresso Blend"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/rsr_2lb_DrDoolittle_900x900_022175eb-3869-4ac7-9d48-17533c43c87a_medium.jpg?v=1547064369" style="float: none;"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/bohemian-gothic-dark-roast-blend?variant=37059154832" title="Bohemian Gothic - Dark Roast Blend"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/RSR-Bag-BohemianGothic-2LB_d7c23837-92cd-4c36-8cd3-8ac8e8abc35c_medium.jpg?v=1565012001" style="float: none;"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/single-origins/products/the-stumbling-monkey-whiskey-barrel-aged-ethiopian-coffee?variant=11202347827236" title="The Stumbling Monkey - Barrel-aged Ethiopian Coffee"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/RSR-Bag-StumblingMonkey-2LB_medium.jpg?v=1565387958" alt=""></a><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/dr-doolittles-espresso-classico-medium-dark-roast-direct-trade-espresso-blend" title="Dr. Doolittle's Espresso Classico - Medium-Dark Roast Espresso Blend"></a></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><em>Photo credit: <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/tU97-ceagL4" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tyler Nix, via Unsplash</a></em></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/specialty-coffee-freshness-prolonging-the-magic</id>
    <published>2019-07-02T12:40:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2020-03-15T11:53:28-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/specialty-coffee-freshness-prolonging-the-magic"/>
    <title>How to store coffee and keep it fresh</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><span>Roaster Brian discusses the factors that contribute to Good Coffee going stale (booooo!), and how to prolong the magic of fresh-roasted specialty coffee (which is our #1 jam).</span><p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/specialty-coffee-freshness-prolonging-the-magic">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Check out the video below where Roaster Brian discusses the factors that impact freshness (and therefore flavor) of roasted coffee, and how to help against the battle of Good Coffee going stale.</p>
<p>TL;DR - Buy fresh roasted coffee, store it well, and consume it before the 1-month mark. You'll be happy.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Y7A8W0-wLDg" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
<h3>Summary of the video</h3>
<ul>
<li>3 factors impacting freshness: Temperature, Humidity, Oxygen</li>
<li>Best storage conditions: Cool &amp; Dry location, in as oxygen-free packaging as possible</li>
<li>Storage in a freezer? - ONLY when you want to keep an sealed/unopened bag fresh for about 1-2 months. Once you open it, keep it in a cool, dry place</li>
<li>Best storage solution: Our 5oz or 12oz bags, or our <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/airscape-2lb-coffee-storage-canister-with-rsr-logo" target="_blank" title="2.5LB Airscape Coffee Storage Canister with RSR Logo" rel="noopener noreferrer">2.5LB Airscape Storage Canster</a>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Our 5oz &amp; 12oz bags are thick-walled to prevent oxygen permeating the bag while sealed, they have 1-way release valves to allow off-gassing that occurs in the days following the roasting process (and let's you squeeze a sealed bag to get a whiff of awesomeness), and they have zippers for re-sealing allowing you to keep out as much oxygen as possible while working through the bag.</p>
<p>For customers who order our larger bags, 2LB &amp; 5LB bags, we also have a great solution for you: <a alt="Airscape 2LB Coffee Storage Canister with RSR Logo" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/airscape-2lb-coffee-storage-canister-with-rsr-logo">The Airscape 2LB Coffee Storage Canister w/ RSR Logo</a> - This wonderful device lets you store up to 2.5 lbs of coffee (or other perishable goods) in a mostly air-free environment. Check out the design:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a alt="Airscape 2LB Coffee Storage Canister with RSR Logo" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/coffee-gear/products/airscape-2lb-coffee-storage-canister-with-rsr-logo"><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Airscape-Kilo-Diagram_large.png?v=1582562948" alt="" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"><br><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/products/RSR_Airscape_2LB_Canister-900x900_large.png?v=1582561000" style="float: none;"></a></p>
<h3>Timeline for "freshness"</h3>
<p>The timeline for what counts as a "fresh" roast is usually given as about 2-4 weeks after the roast date on the bag. After about 4 weeks, even a well-sealed bag of coffee will start to taste flat and not as flavorful when brewed. </p>
<p>We stamp a date on each bag to let you know how long you have to enjoy the awesomeness of fresh-roasted coffee. Never seen a roast date on a bag of grocery store coffee? There's a reason for that: Huge coffee companies don't want you to know how long those beans (or worse: grounds) have been sitting in those bags! :)  </p>
<h3>What's the BEST freshness period?</h3>
<p>Brewing coffee in under 2-4 days after roasting, one can often experience some "off" flavors related to the de-gassing process that takes place for up to 4-5 days after roasting - often experience as a grassy flavor and thinness of body. Different coffees and different roast levels will "set up" faster than others, but from my experience, days 6-12 post-roast are the <em>ideal</em> freshness days. De-gassing will be completed and oxidation hasn't started doing its nasty work on the roasted coffee. </p>
<p>After that, you have 2-4 weeks of well-stored whole bean coffee to stay tasty and awesome. After a month, even in a well-stored environment, enough oxygen will eventually start to rob the coffee of its flavor. </p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-reasons-your-company-needs-to-stop-buying-crappy-coffee</id>
    <published>2019-05-02T14:35:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2019-08-20T17:12:33-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-reasons-your-company-needs-to-stop-buying-crappy-coffee"/>
    <title>3 Reasons Your Company Needs To Stop Buying Crappy Coffee</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian explains why you should stop tolerating terrible coffee at the office.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/3-reasons-your-company-needs-to-stop-buying-crappy-coffee">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p style="float: right;"><img alt="Bad Cofee Face" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/bad-coffee-face_medium.jpg?v=1556825793" style="float: right;">In terms of quality, "free office coffee" is generally one step above the dreaded "church coffee." You know the drill: It's expected, it's there, people drink it for the caffeine, but nobody particularly likes it and often times people openly complain about it. Trust me, I get it: I spent a decade working in Corporate IT and the coffee was <em>always</em> terrible. I've also spent my fair share of time in churches, and the coffee there generally tastes like dirty mop water. In both cases, I've learned to Just Say No.<br><br>Though I left the corporate world behind, I still have sympathy to those who dwell in cubicles or in the newer open format co-working spaces, and I don't want y'all to suffer needlessly.</p>
<p>So here are <strong>Roaster Brian's 3 Reasons Your Company Needs To Stop Buying Crappy Coffee</strong>...</p>
<h3>1. Crappy Coffee Tastes Like Crap</h3>
<p>Obviously, right? Office coffee is usually free to employees because there are huge corporate coffee supply companies out there that specialize in providing the cheapest possible coffee (which correlates to the worst possible tasting coffee) and cheap machines to make a cheap cup of coffee that your company doesn't charge you for. But you do get charged the Crap Tax, because the flavor of cheap coffee is objectively Not Good and your taste buds aren't stupid.</p>
<p>In contrast: Our coffee is Awesome. It's fresh-roasted and delivered directly to your office, and it tastes great. Advantage: Us.</p>
<h3>2. Crappy Coffee Does Not Improve Anyone's Lives</h3>
<p>Coffee is consumed the whole world over, but is only grown in countries with high elevations between the Tropics of Cancer &amp; Capricorn. Commercial or commodity grade coffees are the cheapest and least good-tasting coffees, and those are what go into crappy office coffee. Those coffees also do the least bit of good for coffee growing families and communities, who are very often poor and are subject to global commodity market fluctuations far out of their control. Sometimes the prices they can get for their crop fall below their cost of production, which can literally be the difference between eating and not eating.</p>
<p>In contrast: We buy high-grade Specialty Coffee, where producers get far more money for high quality grades than cheap commodity grades. We also specialize in Direct Relationship coffees, which means even more money goes to producers, farmers, and their families and communities. Advantage: Us.</p>
<meta charset="utf-8">
<p>So if your company is one that prides itself on having a social conscience in addition to wanting to make money, you owe it to yourself to evaluate how your office coffee program lines up with your noble social values. We can deliver quality with a conscience. Huge corporate coffee suppliers can't.</p>
<h3>3. Crappy Coffee Does Not "Add Value" To Your Employees' Work Experience</h3>
<p>Sure caffeine is the most popular legal stimulant drug in the country, and your company benefits from getting you all jacked up on caffeine and being productive for the lowest cost possible to them. But crappy coffee is not a "benefit" to you in the Quality of Work Life category.</p>
<p>In contrast: Enjoying fresh, high-quality coffee at work brings you more than just a dirt-flavored caffeine jolt in the morning. Different roasts, different origins, access to the stories of where the coffees came from - those are not something you'll get from massive coffee supply companies that peddle terrible coffee. Advantage: Us.</p>
<h3>The good news: IT DOESN'T HAVE TO BE THIS WAY</h3>
<p>Have your corporate coffee purchaser <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/pages/contact-us" title="Contact Us page">Contact Us</a> today, to take your coffee game from YUCK to YUM. We can talk about any and all of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<strong>Corporate Discounts</strong> - For offices big &amp; small, we offer volume discounts for our corporate customers</li>
<li>
<strong>Fresh-roasted, Specialty Coffee</strong> (Our bread &amp; butter) - In bulk bags or pre-portioned packs for commercial brewers</li>
<li>
<strong>Cold Brew Coffee &amp;  Kegerators</strong> - Depending on your location, we brew &amp; self-distribute delicious cold brew coffee directly to your office</li>
<li>
<strong>Equipment</strong> - Good Coffee deserves good equipment. Either directly through us, or through our equipment sales &amp; service partners </li>
</ul>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/farmer-derek-klingenberg-goes-to-origin-for-coffee-hugs</id>
    <published>2019-02-20T14:48:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2019-02-20T14:49:05-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/farmer-derek-klingenberg-goes-to-origin-for-coffee-hugs"/>
    <title>Farmer Derek Klingenberg goes to origin for coffee hugs</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Since our start in 2015 we have been privileged to develop direct sourcing relationships with two coffee producers, and our longest relationship has been with <a href="http://goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com" target="_blank" alt="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - Direct Trade Specialty Coffee from Nicaragua" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</a> in the Matagalpa department (state) of Nicaragua, who we ordered our first large shipment of coffee from back at the start.</p>
<p>In March of 2018 we took our first trip to Nicaragua to visit the Gold Mountain folks and tour some farms that produce our coffee, and we even sourced a 90+ cupping Pacamara natural process coffee that went on to win two medals in the Golden Bean North America roasters competition in late 2018.</p>
<p>So it was a real gift to be able to go back again so soon in January of 2019. This time I took a few friends with me, including my business partner/friend/cattle rancher/YouTuber, Farmer Derek Klingenberg. And just yesterday he posted this awesome video on his YouTube channel. Check it out!</p>
<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/f0p9BZROCxA" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/direct-trade-specialty-coffee-at-ross-street-roasting-2018-report</id>
    <published>2019-01-25T09:00:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2019-01-25T09:02:31-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/direct-trade-specialty-coffee-at-ross-street-roasting-2018-report"/>
    <title>Direct Trade Specialty Coffee at Ross Street Roasting: 2018 Report</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian reflects on how Direct Trade coffees and more direct relationships with coffee producers impacted our business in 2018.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/direct-trade-specialty-coffee-at-ross-street-roasting-2018-report">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<meta charset="utf-8"><meta charset="utf-8">
<p>As I type this blog post, I'm getting ready to leave for Nicaragua for my second coffee origin trip, and also the second time I'll get to visit our Direct Trade partner of 3+ years,<span> </span><a href="http://goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com/" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers - Nicaragua Direct Trade Specialty Coffee" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</a>. Last year, we were down in March when the 2017-'18 harvest had been over for about a month, so this trip will be a lot different in terms of what aspects of the green coffee production process we'll be seeing.</p>
<p>Given that, it seems like an appropriate time to look back on the year that just passed us by, and see how we did with our commitment to sourcing high-quality Specialty Coffees through more direct relationships with producers. Coffees that we ultimately offer through our<span> </span><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/direct-trade" title="Direct Trade Coffees from Ross Street Roasting Co.">Direct Trade Coffees</a><span> </span>product category.</p>
<p>But first, it's often helpful to review terms that I use frequently in this business, but take for granted that not all coffee drinkers would know what they mean.<br> </p>
<h3>So what is "Direct Trade," anyway?</h3>
<p>Direct Trade is a term that has been used and abused over the years by coffee companies, and even when used responsibly it can take numerous forms. For us here at RSR, Direct Trade refers to supplier relationships that we have with coffee producers in origin countries who export their own coffees and/or those of partner-farmers, import those coffees to high-consumption countries like the US, store their coffees with a warehousing firm, and then sell their coffees directly to roasters like us.</p>
<p>Usually, roasters source coffee through larger importing companies that house coffees from all over the world and do the work of sourcing with producers, so roasters don't have to. There are benefits to both approaches, and we do make use of relationships with importing companies in our overall green coffee sourcing strategy. But we have a special emphasis on forming and cultivating "Direct Trade" (aka <em>more</em> direct relationships) with producers.</p>
<h3>How'd we do in 2018?</h3>
<p>Now that we know what I'm talking about, here's how we did...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="2018 Direct Trade Coffee report at Ross Street Roasting Co." src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/rsr_direct_trade_infographic_social_post_2_grande.jpg?v=1548426457" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>The short story is: 2018 was an excellent year for our Direct Trade goals! Here are some highlights...</p>
<ol>
<li>Our overall green coffee purchases through direct relationships grew significantly to over half</li>
<li>During our trip to Nicaragua in March 2018, we cupped and purchased on the spot what would eventually became our first award-winning micro-lot coffee, a <a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/direct-trade/products/nicaragua-pacamara-natural-process-award-winning-direct-trade-coffee" title="Pacamara Natural Process - Nicaragua Direct Trade Award-winning Micro-lot">Pacamara Natural Process</a> - which then won Silver &amp; Bronze medals in the Golden Bean North America Roasters Competition in Sept. 2018!</li>
<li>We added our second direct sourcing partner - <a href="https://benchmarkcoffeetraders.com/" target="_blank" title="Benchmark Coffee Traders - Papua New Guinea Direct Trade Specialty Coffees" rel="noopener noreferrer">Benchmark Coffee Traders</a>, Papua New Guinea</li>
<li>We converted our highest volume coffee blend (<a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/bohemian-gothic-dark-roast-blend" title="Bohemian Gothic - Dark Roast 100% Direct Trade Specialty Coffee Gourmet Blend">Bohemian Gothic</a>) to use 100% direct trade components from Nicaragua &amp; Papua New Guinea</li>
<li>
<a href="http://www.peacetreebrewing.com/" target="_blank" title="Peace Tree Brewing Co. - Iowa Craft Beer Brewery: Knoxville, Des Moines, Grinnell" rel="noopener noreferrer">Peace Tree Brewing Co.</a> here in Iowa used a Direct Trade PNG coffee in a new beer, the "Cold Brew Coffee Stout," that's now being bottled and distributed throughout Iowa</li>
<li>In October we also hosted Vikram Patel, founder of Benchmark, on a mini-tour across Iowa to visit some of our customers &amp; friends like Brewhemia in Cedar Rapids, and Peace Tree Brewing in Des Moines</li>
</ol>
<p>In closing, I'm very happy with how our direct relationships developed in 2018. With our new branding released, another trip to Nicaragua next week, and a strategy to keep building our brand (and sales) through our online and wholesale channels, I am very excited to see these relationships continue to deepen and expand. </p>
<p>Thanks, folks, for supporting a small roaster with big dreams and a commitment to working as closely with producers as we can, to bring you awesome coffees and to help coffee producers, their families, and communities improve their livelihoods. </p>
<ol></ol>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/meet-ross-our-new-mascot-logo</id>
    <published>2019-01-01T00:00:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-27T16:41:38-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/meet-ross-our-new-mascot-logo"/>
    <title>Meet Ross: The new face of Ross Street Roasting Co.</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Today marks the first day of a new year - 2019 - and it also marks a new chapter in the story of Ross Street Roasting Co. For the past five months we've been working on a brand refresh for RSR, and in this blog post I'm going to introduce you to the most central &amp; visible part of our new branding...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Ross - RSR mascot &amp; logo" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/rsr_ross_logo_blog_1024x1024_11b770e9-d155-4340-a06c-4627f1f0756d_grande.jpg?v=1546012317" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>Ross is a red-eyed tree frog that is native to tropical forests from southern Veracruz and northern Oaxaca in Mexico, to central Panama and northern Colombia (see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agalychnis_callidryas" target="_blank" title="Red-eyed tree frog Wikipedia article" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wikipedia article</a> for more).</p>
<p>When our branding consultant - Adam Feller of <a href="http://www.aviditycreative.com/" target="_blank" title="Avidity Creative website" rel="noopener noreferrer">Avidity Creative</a> - and I were sitting down to work on the new logo, we looked at a handful of first-round concepts he had come up with to see if any of them jumped out at me. Not seeing anything particularly striking, he then asked me if I had any pictures of anything coffee-related that might be iconic, maybe even animals, and I immediately thought of this...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="Red-eyed tree frog on coffee cherries" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/rsr-frog-600x600_grande.jpeg?v=1546013199" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>This is a photo sent me to almost 2 years ago from Ben Weiner, Founder &amp; CEO of <a href="http://www.goldmountaincoffeegrowers.com/" target="_blank" title="Gold Mountain Coffee Growers homepage" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gold Mountain Coffee Growers</a>, our Direct Trade partner in Nicaragua. We've been buying coffee from Gold Mountain since the beginning of Ross Street Roasting, going on 4 years now. Ben snapped this photo on their flagship farm, Finca Idealista ("Idealist Farm"), which we visited in March of 2018 and will be visiting again at the end of this month.</p>
<p>Adam and I were immediately in love with the frog idea and after a few rounds of artwork based on it, we landed on our new logo and our new mascot: The cute, happy coffee bean frog, Ross.</p>
<p>We did take some creative liberties with the coffee cherries/roasted beans - as a roaster of Specialty Coffee I pride myself on making high-grade, specialty coffee accessible to "normal" coffee drinkers, and it's simply a fact that most coffee drinkers have no idea that coffee beans are seeds from cherries that grow on shrubs/trees in tropical climates. So suspend your disbelief: He's sitting on roasted coffee beans. :) </p>
<p>We're so excited to release Ross into the world. We think he's a great visual reflection of what we love doing: Happily bringing you awesome coffee from awesome producers around the coffee-growing world. </p>
<h3>Looking Back 1 Year Later</h3>
<p>Hey folks - Roaster Brian here, just doing a quick look back on this blog post. We're now one year into the use of our new branding, with our frog mascot - Ross - at the center of that, and it's been <em>great</em> to have such a solid design/branding base to build off of. We've consistently received positive feedback on our logo, product packaging, website, etc. Continued praise and gratitude to Avidity Creative, whom we've continued to work with on product labels, product images, social media posts, and more.</p>
<p>Here's to many more years of success with such an awesome brand!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/branding-and-relationships-the-ross-street-roasting-logos</id>
    <published>2018-12-21T11:58:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-21T14:23:55-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/branding-and-relationships-the-ross-street-roasting-logos"/>
    <title>Branding and Relationships: The Ross Street Roasting logo(s)</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian reflects on logo, branding, and artistic relationships prior to the new branding &amp; logo launch in Jan. 2019<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/branding-and-relationships-the-ross-street-roasting-logos">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><strong>First things first: In January 2019, we will be releasing new branding for Ross Street Roasting.</strong> Same name, same great coffee, but <em>big</em> changes to a lot of other stuff, including our logo. So in advance of that change, I thought I'd write a bit about the logos that have carried us through our first 3.5 years of business.</p>
<p>Before "Ross Street Roasting Co." existed as a legal business entity in the great state of Iowa, it was a name I made up while hobby roasting Specialty Coffee in an old garage on Ross Street in Toledo, Iowa, with my trusty "Heat Gun+Bread Machine" roasting equipment.</p>
<p>Prior to being a coffee roaster, my artistic/creative endeavors were musical in nature. For album projects that my bandmates and I worked on as <em>home</em> recording artists (see a trend here?), we would partner with friends that had more visual-artistic talent than us for album artwork. Adam Wagler - now Assistant Professor of Advertising &amp; Public Relations at the University of Nebraska-Lincoln - was one of those friends, and he's the person who designed the first iteration of the RSR logo in 2014...</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Logo_-_Large_medium.png?v=1545408310" alt="Original RSR logo" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>This logo was essentially the only branding asset we had for our first year of business in 2015, and our coffee bag labels were basically this logo and hand-written product names. As we began to get into more grocery stores and our online presence started to expand, I had the sense that this austere, black &amp; white approach needed a bit more color and visual splash. </p>
<p>So in 2016 I began working with Eddie Gonzalez of <a href="http://schleitheim.com/" target="_blank" title="Schleitheim Designs homepage" rel="noopener noreferrer">Schleitheim Designs</a>, out of Southern California. Eddie and I had collaborated on a book publishing project the year before and I was impressed with his artistic and design chops. The tweak he came up with on the original logo added some color and a "bounded" look that is helpful for logo recognition...</p>
<p><img src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Logo_-_Standard_medium.png?v=1545409523" alt="RSR logo 2016-2018" style="display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"></p>
<p>Eddie and his wife, Kimbrah, also developed the "pastoral scene" artwork that's been used extensively on our bag labels and website/social media profiles since mid-2016...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="RSR farm scene" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/Farm_scene_-_Web_large.jpg?v=1545409839" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>The design logic behind this image was the seamless melding of a Central American coffee farm (left) with a US-Midwestern farm (right). Artistic liberties are taken with roasted coffee beans "growing" in fields like heads of lettuce and like apples on trees in a warm, inviting pastoral scene. I've always loved this piece and I'll be sad to see it retired, though I'm sure we can continue to find ways to incorporate it in the new branding...</p>
<p> </p>
<h3>So where's the new logo?!</h3>
<p>If you're on our email newsletter, you've already had a chance to see it. <em>Nudge, nudge: Signup form is at the bottom of the page ;)</em> - Here on the blog I'll be making another post before the end of the year to introduce the new logo and tell its story (it's got a cool story).</p>
<p>As we prepare to retire the logo and branding assets that have served us well these first 3.5 years, I'd like to thank Adam, Eddie, Kimbrah, Devin Green, Seth Shannon - and all the other folks that have helped create the visual aspects of the Ross Street Roasting Co. brand. Aside from amazing coffee, relationships are what I love most about being in the coffee business, and I take the kinds of relationships above as seriously as I take our coffee sourcing and customer service relationships. I can't take for granted for a second, these folks and their considerable talents, so I say again: Thank you and Big Love to all you folks who've helped so far - And I can't wait to show y'all what's around the corner in 2019!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/farmer-fancy-farmer-derek-klingenberg-drinks-coffee-til-the-cows-come-home</id>
    <published>2018-09-25T15:52:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2018-11-06T19:40:44-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/farmer-fancy-farmer-derek-klingenberg-drinks-coffee-til-the-cows-come-home"/>
    <title>Farmer Fancy: Farmer Derek Klingenberg drinks coffee &apos;til the cows come home</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Ross Street Roasting Co. has covered a lot of territory the past three years. We've even made it to the cattle ranches of central Kansas! Check out Farmer Derek Klingenberg making this Chemex brew of Jack's Feed Store with his dad in their cattle pasture! :) </p>
<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/86xA6KA2njQ" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; encrypted-media" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-stumbling-monkey-his-story</id>
    <published>2018-05-10T11:17:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-10T11:18:06-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/the-stumbling-monkey-his-story"/>
    <title>The Stumbling Monkey: His Story</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Ah, the warm, sweet, oaky smell of bourbon whiskey. If you’re a lover of craft/specialty coffees, chances are good that you also appreciate craft beer and/or spirits. That’s certainly the case for me, which is why as a specialty coffee roaster I’ve been an avid collaborator with craft brewers and distillers in my business. The most popular product of mine from these collaborations is what I call “The Stumbling Monkey,” a bourbon+beer barrel-aged Colombian coffee that I produce twice a year in the spring and fall.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Process</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The first time I produced it, I came up with the name “The Stumbling Monkey” based on the names of the previous uses for the barrel. Originally housing a Wild Turkey bourbon, the oak barrel was then purchased by <a href="http://www.lionbridgebrewing.com/" target="_blank" title="Lion Bridge Brewing Co. - Cedar Rapids, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lion Bridge Brewing Co.</a> in Cedar Rapids, Iowa, an hour from my roastery. Lion Bridge then aged a fall seasonal brown ale and named it “Gobble Wobble.” Thanksgiving...turkey...booze… Get it?! :) - So when the barrel was emptied of beer, I purchased it to age green/un-roasted coffee beans and continued the “inebriated animal” metaphor. The name has been almost as popular as the coffee itself.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">For the Spring 2018 release, we used a bourbon barrel from <a href="https://cedarridgewhiskey.com/" target="_blank" title="Cedar Ridge Whiskey - Swisher, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Cedar Ridge Distillery</a> in nearby Swisher, Iowa, which Lion Bridge then used to age a Russian imperial stout. This is the first time I’ve been able to use an “All Iowa” barrel, and both companies were excited and supportive to see a third local maker keep creating goodness with the barrel.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">My aging process for the un-roasted coffee beans is 4-6 weeks. I load 150lbs (1 whole grain sack) of the beans into the open barrel, re-seal it, set it on its side, and then every other day or so I roll it around my shop floor to help evenly distribute the moisture absorption through the coffee beans. The beans act like dense little sponges, and absorb much of the moisture in the barrel’s interior and extracting moisture from the oak. With so much moisture absorbed from the barrel, this essentially “cashes out” the barrel and prevents any subsequent uses (at least for aging more coffee beans).</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">When unloaded from the barrel, the beans are ready for roasting. Their moisture content has changed significantly in the 4-6 weeks, which does dramatically impact the roasting process, but I’ve developed a roast profile that successfully accounts for this change.</span></p>
<p> </p>
<h3><span style="font-weight: 400;">The Outcome</span></h3>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">So what’s this stuff actually taste like? Well, it’s what I like to call “a complex mouth journey.” There are different aromas and tastes that present themselves at different points of the grinding, brewing, drinking, and finishing process.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">The whole beans and dry grounds give off a strong sweet vanilla and caramel aroma that is a touch boozy. If you’re brewing as pour-over and can smell the wet grounds as the hot water is extracting the oils, you start to pick up on the oak barrel characteristics in the aromatics, along with (still) the booziness. In the cup itself, you taste a balance of chocolate, oak, and vanilla. In the finish, the wood lingers and a slight note of the bourbon becomes apparent. In terms of the roast color spectrum, this is what I call a “Medium-Dark” roast, which tends to highlight the chocolate and oak flavors, and received the widest support from my early taste testers.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">This coffee also makes for an </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">amazing</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> cold brew experience! With a 12-hour cold brew extraction, you’re left with a boozy cold coffee concentrate that lends itself well to milk/cream and sugar...or Bailey’s Irish Cream! :)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Some may be thinking: Why bourbon, </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">then</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> beer, before coffee? My first ever barrel-aging project was a single-use bourbon barrel, and the booziness was </span><i><span style="font-weight: 400;">so</span></i><span style="font-weight: 400;"> intense that it gave the coffee a very hard edge. My second batch introduced beer in between the bourbon and coffee, and my own taste tests along with feedback from repeat tasters indicated that the beer mellowed out and sweetened the overall flavor experience while still maintaining the oak and boozy characteristics.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">All in all, The Stumbling Monkey is an interesting beast from both a production and consumption perspective. It’s a fun project that always gets people excited, so it’s one that I look forward to as a roaster. If it's in season, on the website, and you get your hands on some: I hope you enjoy the mouth journey as much as I enjoyed the production journey!</span></p>
<p><span style="font-weight: 400;">Did you miss it this time around? Don't worry, he'll come stumbling back soon enough! Sign up for our newsletter, so you'll be one of the first ones to know! (Keep scrolling down for that...)</span></p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/ross-street-roasting-iowa-craft-beer-bff-foevah</id>
    <published>2018-01-18T09:11:00-06:00</published>
    <updated>2018-01-18T09:22:56-06:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/ross-street-roasting-iowa-craft-beer-bff-foevah"/>
    <title>Ross Street Roasting + Iowa Craft Beer = BFF Fo&apos;evah</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">
      <![CDATA[Roaster Brian loves Iowa craft beer. This is his love letter to those Iowa craft beer folks he has been privileged to work with and thoroughly enjoys drinking the fruits of their labor.<p><a class="read-more" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/ross-street-roasting-iowa-craft-beer-bff-foevah">More</a></p>]]>
    </summary>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>For those who don't already know, Ross Street Roasting is so-named because I (founder/roaster Brian G.) started home-roasting in my garage in Toledo, which faces Ross Street. For a year and a half before we started this business and I bought a real coffee roaster I stood in that garage with a heat gun in my hand, blasting heat on coffee beans that were being moved around by the dough hook in an electric bread machine pan.</p>
<p>But there's precedent for me doing these DIY/maker/craft kinds of things in garages. Behold...</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/IMG_2788_large.jpg?v=1516285640" style="float: none;"></p>
<p>That's me and my dad in the early 90s, brewing beer in our garage on N. Park St. in my hometown of Prairie City, Iowa. So you can see that I've been a craft beer fan since way before I ever started roasting Specialty Coffee.</p>
<p>Tonight I'm headed down to the <strong><a href="http://www.peacetreebrewing.com/" target="_blank" title="Peace Tree Brewing Co." rel="noopener noreferrer">Peace Tree Brewing Co.</a></strong> Grinnell Branch/taproom for the release of a Coffee Stout that their head brewmaster, Joe Kesteloot, and I worked on. I actually haven't tasted it yet, but reports from inside the brewery have been good!</p>
<p>I've had a soft spot for Peace Tree because they started out in Knoxville, Iowa, a town not much bigger than Tama-Toledo and it's very close to where I grew up in Prairie City. Founded in 2009, Peace Tree was one of the first of the latest wave of micro-breweries to start in the state, and they've achieved some great success in a relatively short time. Their owner, Megan McKay, has become a role model for me as a small-town entrepreneur who began with a focus on craft and quality, but then scaled it far beyond their small town.</p>
<p>In the past year we've also done coffee beer projects with two Cedar Rapids-based craft breweries - <strong><a href="http://www.lionbridgebrewing.com" target="_blank" title="Lion Bridge Brewing Co. - Cedar Rapids, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lion Bridge Brewing Co.</a></strong> (a coffee kölsch that was dynamite) &amp; <strong><a href="http://iowabrewing.beer/" target="_blank" title="Iowa Brewing Co. - Cedar Rapids, Iowa" rel="noopener noreferrer">Iowa Brewing Co.</a></strong> (the "Covfefe Brown Ale") - and those projects have been a lot of fun. Working with craft beer brewers is a blast, because in our respective beverages we're always chasing the flavor unicorn. We're trying to get the best flavors out of our ingredients, trying to stay true to traditions &amp; crafts, while also innovating and creating new flavor experiences for those who respect our crafts and enjoy the fruits of our labor.</p>
<p>And besides coffee beers, we also did two barrel-aging projects last year working through Lion Bridge to secure the barrels. The second one last fall - The Stumbling Money, a bourbon barrel-aged Colombian coffee - took a bourbon barrel that then had Lion Bridge's (delicious) Gobble Wobble imperial brown ale, before I finally got it and aged the un-roasted coffee beans in it for a month. The result was a well-rounded sweet, chocolatey, boozy, and barrel-y masterpiece that sold out in just over a month. (Don't worry, we'll be doing more soon!) Just this month I even started experimenting with dry-hopping un-roasted coffee beans, aging hops and beans together prior to roasting. Stay tuned for the results of that alchemy!</p>
<p>To close, I just want to say that being able to collaborate with awesome, kind, smart, passionate people in a craft that I love almost as much (okay, maybe just as much) as Specialty Coffee is a true joy and privilege. It makes my job that I already love that much more enjoyable. Thanks, Iowa craft beer peeps. And thanks to my dad for showing me at a young age how much fun making stuff in your garage can be. :) </p>
<p>Cheers!</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/tama-cedar-rapids-business-ties-run-deep</id>
    <published>2017-11-02T09:27:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2017-11-02T09:31:44-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/tama-cedar-rapids-business-ties-run-deep"/>
    <title>Tama-Cedar Rapids business ties run deep</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p style="float: right;">Earlier this year our friends at <a href="http://brewhemia.com/" target="_blank" title="Brewhemia website" rel="noopener noreferrer">Brewhemia</a> in Cedar Rapids bought into Ross Street Roasting Co., becoming an equity owner and active business partner to me, founder/roaster Brian Gumm. Brewhemia co-owner, Steve Shriver, is also president &amp; founder of <a href="https://ecolips.com/" target="_blank" title="Eco Lips website" rel="noopener noreferrer">Eco Lips</a>, makers of Organic &amp; Fair Trade lip care products.</p>
<p style="float: right;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/664920_135542316593839_2079270097_o-500x333_49a362c1-b789-4a7e-92dd-c11e2a1e0b0b_medium.jpg?v=1509632089" style="float: right; margin-left: 5px;">Both Brewhemia and Eco Lips are located in the New Bohemia district just south of downtown Cedar Rapids, an area that was decimated by the 2008 floods and has been dramatically redeveloped in the 9 years since. Eco Lips is located in the Cherry Building, which originally housed the J.G. Cherry Company, a dairy industry supply company that started in the late 1800s. <br><br>Last night my wife and I attended a presentation by a local historian about two famous houses in Tama-Toledo, one of which is locally known as "Cherry Mansion." I had known about this house and its name for most of the 5 years that I've lived here, but didn't really know why it was called that. Well, last night I learned that it was named after two long-time residents of the house, <a href="https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=120460706" target="_blank" title="Herbert Tilden obituary" rel="noopener noreferrer">Herbert Tilden</a> and <a href="https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=122708391" target="_blank" title="Louise Cherry obituary" rel="noopener noreferrer">Helen Louise</a> Cherry.</p>
<p style="float: left;"><img alt="" src="https://images.findagrave.com/photos/2016/82/120460706_1458792253.jpg" style="float: left; margin-right: 5px;">As the local historian was describing the Cherry family, she pointed out that Herbert had come from Cedar Rapids and the family often spent time there, and also frequently had friends coming to visit their Tama home from Cedar Rapids. <br><br>And a thought occurred to me: "Wait...a Cherry from Cedar Rapids. Eco Lips is in the Cherry Building in NewBo...?"<br><br>With a bit of googling, I discovered that there is indeed a family connection. Herbert's father was <a href="https://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;GRid=111107822" target="_blank" title="J.G. Cherry obituary" rel="noopener noreferrer">John George (J.G.) Cherry</a>. Herbert worked for his father's company upon graduating from high school in 1888, and in 1914 he was sent to Tama upon the company's acquisition of a paper factory here (which is still in operation 3 blocks from the roastery). Upon acquisitions of other paper companies in the region, Herbert served as president of that merged entity from 1931-1945.</p>
<p>Herbert passed away in 1949 at the age of 71. His wife, Louise, passed away in 1965 at the age of 83. They were both well-regarded and remembered for their abundant generosity and support of the local community, and for their hospitality. There are people living today who recall Halloween parties hosted by Mrs. Cherry, and I even saw a few color photos of one from the late 50s/early 60s before her death.</p>
<p>From the start of this business, I have intentionally networked with the urban centers that surround Tama-Toledo an hour in every direction, especially Cedar Rapids. That networking eventually resulted in a business relationship, and I thought I was being a savvy rural entrepreneur at the time for seeking such partnerships.</p>
<p>But the Ecclesiastes principle still applies: There is nothing new under the sun. My partners in Cedar Rapids and I are merely standing in a line stretching back over a century. It's humbling to make such discoveries, and exciting as well. It gives me a deeper sense of belonging in the place we call home.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/ross-street-raygun-a-prrrrfect-pairing</id>
    <published>2017-10-03T11:11:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2017-10-03T11:15:00-05:00</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/blogs/roasters-blog/ross-street-raygun-a-prrrrfect-pairing"/>
    <title>Ross Street &amp; Raygun: A prrrrfect pairing</title>
    <author>
      <name>Brian Gumm</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      <![CDATA[<p>Hey y'all - Roaster Brian here...</p>
<p>I first heard about <a href="https://raygunsite.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">RAYGUN</a> when I still lived in the Des Moines area back in the ought's. I believe it may have been the ought-six or -seven. Anyway, my sister-in-law who works downtown and has her finger on all the cool DSM happenings told me about this new t-shirt company that had started up and was making hilarious and awesome tee's with inside jokes about Des Moines and Iowa.</p>
<p>Their punny, snarky aesthetic was right up my alley, so there's been a stack of RAYGUN tee's in my family's closets ever since.</p>
<p>So earlier this year when my biz partner, Steve Shriver, said "Let's talk to RAYGUN about selling coffee!," I was immediately all in. Emails were exchanged. Ideas were pitched. Excitement ensued. A really tasty coffee was born:</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><a href="https://www.rossstreetroasting.com/collections/blends/products/meow-thats-what-i-call-light-roast-raygun-collaboration-light-roast-coffee-blend">Meow That's What I Call Light Roast!</a></h3>
<p style="float: right;"><img alt="" src="//cdn.shopify.com/s/files/1/1505/8342/files/meowlightroast_12oz_4_be005bde-b301-4fb4-9545-03d796631e6c_large.jpg?v=1506110451" style="float: right;">Here's how RAYGUN founder, Mike Draper, tells it: "We told Brian, ‘Take a look at this store, and make a blended coffee that tastes like the store looks.’ A couple weeks later, Brian came back with this blend. We tasted it and said, ‘Yes, exactly. This tastes just like the store looks: amazing.’”</p>
<p style="float: right;">As for the product name itself, here's how the fictional cat Gary adorning the front label remembers it: “I’ve always preferred Chivas Regal to coffee. I’ve also been known to experiment with mescaline — though it’s been a while. But when I tasted Brian’s coffee I said, ‘<em>Meow </em>That’s What I Call Light Roast!’ I drink it straight, or with a little bit of Chivas Regal and mescaline. Tastes great either way.” </p>
<p>There you have it, folks: The origin story of a great pairing of two Iowa companies that make claw-some stuff, teaming up to make even claw-somer stuff together. And we now have a coffee with cat-itude. We love it. We hope you do, too.</p>]]>
    </content>
  </entry>
</feed>
